{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This politician called Russia “a riddle, wrapped up in a mystery, inside an enigma.” The\nfailure of the Gallipoli Campaign tarnished the early career of this orator who capped off his best\nspeeches with phrases like “blood, toil, tears, and sweat” and “this was their finest hour.” Taking\noffice after Neville Chamberlain resigned, this politician led his country through the Battle of\nBritain. For 10 points, name this Prime Minister who led Britain through most of World War II.",
      "answer": [
        "Winston Churchill",
        "Churchill",
        "Sir Winston Leonard Spencer-Churchill"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One side at this battle found its only significant success through an assault on a baggage train\nand was hindered by enemy palings. One side at this battle had previously besieged Harfleur. An\ninitial cavalry charge in this battle failed miserably and churned the field with mud, thus\nimpairing subsequent advances on foot by forces led by the Constable of France. For 10 points,\nname this English victory for Henry V in the Hundred Years War thanks to the efficiency of\nlongbows.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Agincourt",
        "Agincourt"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This party controlled government during the Thirteen Wasted Years. It lost power in 1974\nwith the failure of leader Edward Heath, but regained it when its opponents suffered the “Winter\nof Discontent.” In the 1980s, this party dealt with a miners’ strike in its efforts to weaken unions\nand privatize state industries. For 10 points, name this British political party once led by\nMargaret Thatcher, which opposes the Labour Party.",
      "answer": [
        "Conservative Party",
        "Conservatives",
        "Tories"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "For her role during this period, Marina Mniszech entered folklore as Marinka the Witch. Kuzma Minin and Dmitry Pozharsky became patriotic heroes for defeating a Polish army during this period after raising funds from the city of Nizhny Novgorod. No fewer than three men were killed after falsely claiming to be the deceased Tsarevich Dmitri during this period. For 10 points, name this period of civil disorder in Russia that ended with the establishment of the Romanov Dynasty.",
      "answer": "the Time of Troubles"
    },
    {
      "question": "After a series of competitions in this sport, two sides engaged in mutual popular boycott after controversy over the Adelaide leak and the bodyline tactic. That tactic neutralized the prowess of one of the greatest athletes to play this sport, Don Bradman, and was part of The Ashes series between England and Australia. This sport has Twenty20, One Day International, and Test varieties. For 10 points, name this sport popular in the British Commonwealth that uses a flat bat and wickets.",
      "answer": "cricket"
    },
    {
      "question": "A painting by Jacques-Louis David shows this man receiving alms while a soldier watches, astonished. Procopius recounts the lurid tale of this man being cuckolded by his adopted son Theodosius. This man's greatest victories include beating the Sassanids at Dara and the Vandals at Tricamarum [try-CAM-er-UM]. This man's first Italian campaign ended after an offer to be made emperor aroused Justinian's suspicions. For 10 points, name this Byzantine general who reconquered Italy and much of North Africa for the empire.",
      "answer": "Belisarius"
    },
    {
      "question": "This person first came to power under the tutelage of Concino Concini, who was killed due to the influence of Charles de Luynes. He led the attempt to capture La Rochelle, making Huguenots sign the Peace of Alais. He was the target of the Day of the Dupes, when Marie de Medici attempted to have him removed. He led the French cause in the Thirty Years War and was replaced by Mazarin after his death. For 10 points, name this cardinal who advised Louis XIII.",
      "answer": "Cardinal Richelieu"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Neutral White Cross was established to provide medical relief during this period. The U.S. intervened to stop the German ship Ypiranga from arming militants in this conflict. Venustiano Carranza held the Convention of Aguascalientes during this period, which was ushered in by the Plan of San Luis Potosi. The Ten Tragic Days, which resulted in the assassination of Francisco Madero, took place during, for ten points, what decade-long revolution that began with the ousting of Porfirio Diaz and whose military actions ended with the pacification of Pancho Villa?",
      "answer": "Mexican Revolution"
    },
    {
      "question": "Sigmund Rascher’s experiments were used to test technology for this military force. Members of this group carried out the Stalag Luft III murders after a group of Allied POWs escaped from one of their prisons. Its leader committed suicide after being sentenced to death during the Nuremberg Trials. The Junkers [yoon-kers] Ju-87 was heavily used by this organization for dive-bombing. Herman Goering led, for ten points, what branch of the Nazi military that bombed Britain?",
      "answer": [
        "Luftwaffe",
        "the Nazi German Air Force"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Russian Empire used Agvan Dorzhiev as a contact to one of these people. One of these people fled in response to a military expedition led by Francis Younghusband, and his successor called for a democratic “zone of peace” in his Strasbourg proposal. These people are said to be reincarnations of Avalokitesvara, and the most recent of these people went to exile in India after a 1959 uprising was crushed by Chinese forces. For ten points, name this position currently held by Tenzin Gyatso, the leader of Tibetan Buddhism.",
      "answer": "Dalai Lamas"
    },
    {
      "question": "Wisconsin’s John Blaine was the only senator to vote against ratification of this agreement, which the Senate interpreted to protect the right to self-defense. Sixty-two countries ultimately signed this agreement, which was criticized for having no effective means of enforcement, as seen by Italy’s invasion of Ethiopia in 1935. For ten points, name this 1928 agreement, named for a US Secretary of State and French Foreign Minister, whose signatories renounced the use of war in national policy.",
      "answer": [
        "Kellogg-Briand Pact",
        "Pact of Paris"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This battle’s concluding skirmishes in the Ancre valley were called off on account of the winter. Operation Alberich saw a strategic retreat from the front lines of this battle. An explosion at Hawthorne Ridge during this battle was filmed by Geoffrey Malins. Ferdinand Foch and Douglas Haig failed to make significant breakthroughs in the German line during this battle during the winter of 1916. The tank was first utilized at, for ten points, what deadly World War I battle, in which over 600,000 allied troops were killed in fighting for a French river?",
      "answer": "Battle of the Somme"
    },
    {
      "question": "One supporter of these people launched the failed Atterbury Plot. An uprising of these people is the subject of the song “Johnny Cope.” These people launched the failed “Forty-Five” uprising which was defeated at the Battle of Culloden. These people believed in the legitimacy of Bonnie Prince Charlie to the throne. For ten points, name these people who claimed that the House of Stuart were the legitimate heirs to the British throne.",
      "answer": "Jacobites"
    },
    {
      "question": "Alfred Blunt, Bishop of Bradford, delivered an address against this event and advocated “divine grace” for its subject. A missed meeting at the Aberdeen Royal Infirmary helped fan suspicion about this event. Walter Monckton assisted with the legal issues of this event, and Stanley Baldwin blocked an attempt by this event’s perpetrator to address the nation. Socialite Wallis Simpson provoked, for ten points, what 1936 event, the only formal renunciation of the throne since the Anglo-Saxon period?",
      "answer": [
        "abdication of Edward VIII",
        "synonyms for “abdicate,” such as Edward VIII giving up the British throne before “formal” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Members of this ruler’s court were tried for treason in the Merciless Parliament. One of this ruler’s supporters, Robert de Vere, was defeated outside of Oxford by the forces of the Lords Appellant. This ruler was succeeded by the son of John of Gaunt. This son of Edward the Black Prince attempted to collect poll taxes, leading to Wat Tyler’s Peasants’ Revolt. For ten points, name this last Plantagenet King of England who was forced to abdicate by Henry IV, leading to the War of the Roses.",
      "answer": "Richard III of England"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler put down a revolt in Ghent against his sister, Mary of Hungary. The Battle of Villalar was one episode in an uprising against this man called the Revolt of the Comuneros. He renounced his claim to Burgundy in the “Ladies’ Peace” of Cambrai. His army captured Francis I at the Battle of Pavia, and he condemned Martin Luther at the Diet of Worms. For ten points, name this man who ruled as Holy Roman Emperor and King of Spain.",
      "answer": [
        "Charles V",
        "Charles I of Spain",
        "Charles I of Austria"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Sopwith Camels were equipped with two of these devices, often produced by Lewis. The capture of Roland Garros’ equipment helped German engineers like Anthony Fokker develop synchronization gear, permitting these closed-bolt weapons to operate through the gaps of a spinning propeller. The Browning M1919 replaced many Vickers-produced examples of, for ten points, what weapons that were mounted on World War I-era aircraft and could fire hundreds of bullets per minute?",
      "answer": "machine gun"
    },
    {
      "question": "A character in this play claims that a sunburn could not make his face any worse looking. In this play, it is said that Arthur’s bosom is the destination of the dead Falstaff. At a charge at Harfleur, this play’s title character declares “Once more unto the breach,” and later uses the phrase “we few, we happy few, we band of brothers” to open the St. Crispin’s Day Speech. For ten points, name this Shakespeare history play about the British king who won the Battle of Agincourt.",
      "answer": "Henry V do not"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man liberated Bulgaria from 400 years of Ottoman rule following a successful siege of Pleven. He employed Dmitri Milyutin to open army recruitment to all social classes, and he encouraged the new zemstvo system of local government. Loris-Melikov’s work with this leader to establish a parliament was thwarted when this leader was assassinated by the People’s Will in St. Petersburg. For ten points, name this Russian tsar who emancipated the serfs.",
      "answer": "Alexander II"
    },
    {
      "question": "A shipment of arms to this group aboard the Eksund was intercepted by the French and discovered to have been sent by Muammar Gaddafi. Bobby Sands died in a hunger strike protesting the prison rights afforded to members of this group, which began to disarm after Sinn Fein [shin fayn] signed the Good Friday Accords with Tony Blair. For ten points, name this paramilitary group that split off from an “Official” nonviolent group shortly after “The Troubles” began in Ireland.",
      "answer": "Provisional Irish Republican Army or PIRA"
    },
    {
      "question": "As a result of this treaty, Portugal regained Colonia do Sacramento in Uruguay. This treaty forced North American tribes formerly loyal to France to open trade with all nations. Britain increased its hold on the slave market when it was given the asiento, along with Gibraltar, in this treaty. Philip, duke of Anjou, renounced his claim to the French throne as a result of, for ten points, what treaty that ended the War of the Spanish Succession?",
      "answer": "Treaty of Utrecht"
    },
    {
      "question": "Louis-Antoine Beaunier received a royal commission to construct one of these structures to aid the mining industry in the Loire basin. The first of these structures in Paris started at the Gare du Nord. Saint-E´tienne was an early center for these structures, which were financed by the Perri`ere brothers through the Cr´edit Mobilier. In 1937, these systems were nationalized in France under the SNCF, which still runs them today. For ten points, name these structures, which link cities like Lyon and Paris.",
      "answer": "French railways"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man formulated Operation Paukenschlag, part of a military plan also known as the “Second Happy Time.” This man issued a command to disregard drowning sailors after the a B-24 bomber attacked a ship carrying survivors of the Laconia. This head of state under the Flensburg government pioneered “wolfpack” tactics in the Battle of the Atlantic. For ten points, name this admiral who advocated for unlimited U-boat warfare, then surrendered to the Allies after he was named Adolf Hitler’s successor as President of Germany.",
      "answer": "Karl D¨onitz"
    },
    {
      "question": "This battle was prompted by faulty intelligence that claimed one side was at Fort Ninety-Six. While attempting to taunt the enemy commander, William Washington had his horse shot out from under him. In this battle, John Eager Howard helped form one of three lines of defense set up by the Broad River to repel an attack from the British Legion under Banastre Tarleton. For ten points, name this 1781 Revolutionary War victory for Daniel Morgan in South Carolina.",
      "answer": "Battle of Cowpens"
    },
    {
      "question": "William Thomas Turner attempted to prevent this disaster, which occurred near the Old Head of Kinsale. The Cunard Company was prosecuted for its negligence surrounding this event, since it failed to reveal that munitions had been placed in storage. William Jennings Bryan resigned as Secretary of State because he felt Woodrow Wilson was too strong-handed in his reaction to, for ten points, what 1915 event in which a British ocean liner was torpedoed by a German U-boat?",
      "answer": "sinking of or attack on, etc. the RMS Lusitania"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this period, accused parties were ordered to prove their innocence by the Law of 22 Prairial, which strengthened the Law of Suspects. This period came to an end when the Battle of Fleurus helped trigger the Thermidorian Reaction against one of this period’s leaders. The Committee of Public Safety took control during this period, which ended with Maximilien Robespierre’s own execution. For ten points, name this year-long phase of the French Revolution in many political enemies were guillotined.",
      "answer": [
        "Reign of Terror or The Terror",
        "La Terreur"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Hugh Trenchard is nicknamed the “father of” this military force, which sustained heavy casualties in Bloody April during the Battle of Arras. The efforts of this military force prompted the declaration “Never was so much owed by so many to so few.” This force employed the Sopwith Camel during World War I and the Supermarine Spitfire during World War II. For ten points, name this military force that battled the Luftwaffe to defend cities like Coventry and London.",
      "answer": [
        "Royal Air Force or RAF",
        "Royal Flying Corps",
        "descriptions of the air force of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland,",
        "British Air Force,",
        "similar"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these phenomena, nicknamed the “mud-eater” for its effects on Provence’s agriculture, is known as the mistral. William of Orange’s invasion of England was enabled by a so-called “Protestant” version of this phenomenon, which also destroyed Philip II’s Armada, preventing a Spanish takeover. The Portuguese used the term “volto de mar” to describe their caravels being powered by, for ten points, what meteorological phenomenon that powers sailing ships?",
      "answer": [
        "winds",
        "close equivalents like storm, but not “rain”",
        "mistral before mentioned",
        "Protestant wind after “William” is mentioned",
        "tradewinds after “volto” is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "To prepare for this battle, the winning commander designed a namesake “chequer” of yellow and black lines to better identify his ships. A tactic mirroring John Jervis’ maneuvers at Cape St. Vincent was employed at this battle to isolate the Bucentaure. The destruction of a Franco-Spanish navy at this battle ended Napoleon’s hopes of invading England. For ten points, name this 1805 victory for Lord Nelson, commemorated in a namesake London Square.",
      "answer": "Battle of Trafalgar"
    },
    {
      "question": "As a teenager, this thinker built a calculator to aid his father’s work as a tax supervisor. This man developed a law stating that a change in pressure at a point in a fluid is transmitted equally throughout the entire fluid. This man, who argued in support of Jansenism in Provincial Letters, names a diagram that conveniently displays the binomial coefficients; each value equals the sum of the two numbers above it in that “triangle.” For ten points, name this 17th century French polymath.",
      "answer": "Blaise Pascal"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Pont Neuf was completed during the reign of this French monarch; its financing was overseen by this man’s chief minister, Maximilien de Bethune, the Duke of Sully. This king’s mistress, Gabrielle d’Estr´ees [dess-tray], supposedly convinced him to proclaim that Paris was “well worth a mass” when he converted from Protestantism to Catholicism. For ten points, name this king who supported religious toleration via the Edict of Nantes, the first monarch from the House of Bourbon.",
      "answer": [
        "Henry IV",
        "Henry III of Navarre, but"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A treaty with this name included the secret Act of Seclusion, by which the future William III lost the title of Stadtholder. The first and third Anglo-Dutch Wars were ended by treaties of this name. A 1931 statute of this name established protocols between the U.K. and dominion realms. A religious building with this name was built on the orders of Edward the Confessor and was the site of his burial. For ten points, give the name shared by the abbey where British monarchs are coronated.",
      "answer": [
        "Westminster",
        "Treaty of Westminster",
        "Statute of Westminster",
        "Westminster Abbey"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "These people were the target of a seawall built by Pompeo Targone, which withstood an assault from Henri de Rohan. A leader of these people, Gaspard de Coligny, was killed on the orders of Catherine de Medici during the St. Bartholomew’s Day Massacre. These followers of John Calvin were stripped of their religious tolerance by the Edict of Fontainebleau, many years after it was first granted by Henry IV’s Edict of Nantes. For ten points, name this group of French Protestants.",
      "answer": "Huguenots"
    },
    {
      "question": "Negotiations for this treaty occurred concurrently with those of the Treaty of Hubertusburg. Charles III’s refusal to cede Cuba led to Spain relinquishing Florida as part of this agreement, which was largely negotiated by the Duc de Choiseul. In this treaty, Guadalupe and Martinique were kept by a party that ceded all of its mainland holdings west of the Mississippi River. Much of New France was ceded to England in, for ten points, what treaty ending the Seven Years’ War?",
      "answer": "1763 Treaty of Paris"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man rose to his highest post after Milan Gorkic was assassinated by secret police. He emerged victorious in a power struggle with Draza Mihailovic’s Chetniks. This man was eventually expelled from Cominform after his style of socialism led to a break with Joseph Stalin, so he instead served as the European leader of the Non-Aligned movement. For ten points, name this marshal who led Yugoslavia following World War II.",
      "answer": "Josip Broz Tito"
    },
    {
      "question": "Inthis US state, Augustus Stinchfield partneredwith a British man toform a private medical practice. Miners flocked to this state following a discovery in its Vermilion Range. Charles Alfred Pillsbury founded his namesake company in this state, where its flour mills competed with rival General Mills. Iron ore from mountains in this state was transported by train to cities like Duluth. The Mayo Clinic was founded in Rochester in, for ten points, what US state where 3M is headquartered in a suburb of St. Paul?",
      "answer": "Minnesota"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event, which inspired Michael Tippet’s oratorio A Child of Our Time, caused many people to flee to the Restricted Sector for Stateless Refugees in Shanghai. Reinhard Heydrich sent a secret telegram with instructions for this event, which included the arrests of tens of thousands of men. This event began on November 9th, exactly fifteen years after the Beer Hall Putsch, and featured mass looting of stores and burning of synagogues. For ten points, name this 1938 attack on German Jews, named for the shards of glass that flew during it.",
      "answer": [
        "Kristallnacht",
        "Night of Broken Glass before “glass” is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man agreed to a truce with England in the Treaty of Picquigny, allowing him to focus his forces against the League of the Public Weal. This man revolted against his father in the failed Praguerie and subsequently fled to Philip the Good’s court. After his greatest foe was slain at Nancy, this ruler annexed Picardy. The death of Charles the Bold allowed this man to take control of Burgundy. For ten points, name this French monarch whose diplomatic cunning earned him his nickname.",
      "answer": [
        "Louis XI",
        "Louis the Prudent",
        "Louis the Universal Spider"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A key leader of this movement had a brother who helped win the Battle of Ayacucho and founded the newspaper Northern Star. This movement included striking miners in Cornwall in the Plug Plot Riots. Feargus O’Connor led this movement, which indirectly increased suffrage via the 1867 Great Reform Bill. This movement called for secret ballots and annual elections for Parliament. For ten points, name this 19th century British working class movement for political reform that called for the vote for all men over age 21.",
      "answer": [
        "Chartism",
        "word forms, like Chartists"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An infamous doctrine developed by this man prevented the extradition of terrorists back to Italy. This man signed the Gayssot Act to make denial of the Holocaust illegal. This man controversially ordered Operation Satan, the bombing of the Greenpeace ship Rainbow Warrior in New Zealand waters. This leader’s tenure featured two cohabitations with Edouard Balladur and Jacques Chirac. For ten points, name this first socialist president of France.",
      "answer": "Francois Mitterand"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man worked with the ambassador Michel Ange Bernard de Mangourit during his most famous venture, which began when he arrived aboard the Embuscade in Charleston Harbor. This man attempted to hire the Anti-George and other privateers to help his country in a war against Spain and Britain, a stance opposed by George Washington. For ten points, name this Frenchman whose namesake affair tested American neutrality.",
      "answer": [
        "Edmond-Charles Genˆet",
        "Citizen Genˆet"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization ran an espionage training program whose students included Ernst Wollweber and which was known as M School. A 1929 conflict pitted the forces of Zhang Xueliang against this organization. While serving as the leader of this organization, Mikhail Tukhachevsky faced an uprising of sailors in the Kronstadt Rebellion. Forces of this organization fought against neighboring Finland in the Winter War. For ten points, name this force that fought the White Army in the Russian Civil War.",
      "answer": "Workers’ and Peasants’ Red Army"
    },
    {
      "question": "This battle was the site of an alleged last stand at La Belle Alliance where one unit declared “the Guard dies, it does not surrender.” The Lion’s Mound monument commemorating this battle overlooks the house of La Haye Sainte. The arrival of Gebhard von Blucher’s Prussians helped decide this battle, which forced its losing commander into exile at Saint Helena. For ten points, name this 1815 battle in which Napoleon was defeated for the final time.",
      "answer": "Battle of Waterloo"
    },
    {
      "question": "The British worked to replace this material with cordite in the 19th century. One of the earliest descriptions of this substance is in the Wujing Zongyao, an 11th century military compendium. The Mughals, Safavids, and Ottomans were known as the empires of this substance, which is made of sulfur, charcoal, and saltpeter. For ten points, name this one of the Four Great Inventions of China, an explosive material that revolutionized ranged warfare.",
      "answer": "gunpowder"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man signaled his newfound status by changing his last name to include “Novyi.” Enemies of this man accused him of joining the Khlysty sect. This man was lured into the Moika Palace on the night of his downfall, and when he drank Felix Yusupov’s cyanide-laced wine without any effect, he was shot three times. This man had gained royal influence due to his apparent ability to stop the bleeding of Alexei, the hemophiliac heir of the tsar. For ten points, name this Russian mystic who advised Nicholas II.",
      "answer": "Grigori Rasputin"
    },
    {
      "question": "Karl Radek argued against signing this treaty, arguing that revolutions would soon occur that would render it unnecessary. This treaty, whose terms were annulled in the Treaty of Rapallo, made the Kars Oblast an Ottoman territory. Demands for “peace, land, and bread” fueled one side to accept the harsh terms of this treaty, which included giving control of the Baltic States to Germany. For ten points, name this 1918 treaty that took Russia out of World War I.",
      "answer": "Treaty of Brest-Litovsk"
    },
    {
      "question": "These people were able to place a poster on a monarch’s bedchamber door at Amboise [am-BWAHZ] in the Affair of the Placards. These people, who attempted to settle Fort Caroline, were massacred two days after an attack on one of them, Gaspard de Coligny. Catherine de Medici probably ordered the St. Bartholomew’s Day Massacre against these people, the subjects of Louis XIV’s Edict of Fontainebleau and Henry IV’s Edict of Nantes. For ten points, name this group of French Calvinists.",
      "answer": "Huguenots"
    },
    {
      "question": "One leader of this kingdom was called the “mute king,” and a curse believed to be cast on the ruling dynasty of this kingdom supposedly explains why alternating generations of its Wadiyar Dynasty never hadchildren.Thefirstiron-casedrocketswereusedbythiskingdom,leadingtheBritishtoreverse-engineer the Congreve Rocket. This kingdom’s ruler Hyder Ali fought the Maratha Confederacy and the British East India Company. Tipu Sultan ruled, for ten points, what kingdom in southern India?",
      "answer": "Kingdom of Mysore"
    },
    {
      "question": "The perpetrators of this event avoided jail after a report sent by Aaron Briggs was not believed by Governor Joseph Wanton. Prior to this event, William Dudingston sparked anger by rerouting a rum shipment from the Fortune. The target of this event had run aground while chasing the Hannah near Warwick, allowing John Brown and Abraham Whipple to burn it down. For ten points, name this early act of colonial violence, a 1772 attack on a British vessel in Rhode Island.",
      "answer": "Gaspee Affair"
    },
    {
      "question": "One side was enticed to initiate this battle after intercepting secret messages aboard the ship Automedon. During this battle, the Alexandra Hospital massacre was perpetrated after one side broke through a defense line that allegedly contained coastal guns facing the wrong way. After Arthur Percival’s much larger army was forced to surrender at this battle, Winston Churchill decried it as “the worst disaster” in British military history. For ten points, name this World War II battle for a city south of the Malay Peninsula.",
      "answer": "Battle of Singapore"
    },
    {
      "question": "This general’s Philipsburg Proclamation offered fugitive slaves freedom upon joining the British Army. This general assumed his highest post after a large party known as the Mischianza was thrown for his predecessor. In an attempt to relieve Burgoyne, this man led the capture of Fort Montgomery and dismantled the Hudson River Chain. This man was succeeded by Guy Carleton in his highest post in 1782 after the defeat of General Cornwallis at the Battle of Yorktown. For ten points, name this Commander-in-Chief of British forces in North America after William Howe.",
      "answer": "Henry Clinton"
    },
    {
      "question": "The accused spy David Redding was hanged in what is now this state. Leaders from what is now this state negotiated with representatives of George Germain but failed to reach terms with Quebec governor Frederick Haldimand. This state celebrates Jonathan Stark's defeat of British forces before Saratoga on Bennington Battle Day. In 1791, this state became the 14th state to enter the Union, ending its Republic. For ten points, name this state for which Bernie Sanders has served as Senator.",
      "answer": "Vermont"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's navy beat the Earl of Torrington and Ralph Delaval at the Battle of Beachy Head, preventing an invasion after his army won at Fleurus [[FLOOR-us]]. This man's attempts to install William von Furstenburg in Cologne [[ko-LOHN]] led to the creation of the League of Augsburg. This man gained Alsace and the Rhine River border with Germany at the Treaty of Ryswick [[RIZ-wik]]. This man revoked the Edict of Nantes and was served by Cardinal Mazarin. For ten points, name this Sun King of France.",
      "answer": "Louis XIV or Louis the Great"
    },
    {
      "question": "This body's internal structure was studied using the HP3 heat probe aboard the InSight lander in 2018. In 2022, the European/Russian-designed Rosalind Franklin is scheduled to land on this body. In 1877, Giovanni Schiaparelli [[skap-ah-REH-lee]] claimed to be able to see artificial canals on the surface of this body. Opportunity and Curiosity are two of the rovers which have landed on this body. The Perseverance rover searches for signs of ancient life on, for ten points, what fourth planet from the sun?",
      "answer": "Mars 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 2"
    },
    {
      "question": "An \"Incident\" including the name of this month, perpetrated by the Cherry Blossom Society, attempted to abolish the liberal Taisho democracy in favor of the Showa Restoration. This month names a “Crisis” in which Pierre Trudeau was forced to enact the War Measures Act in Quebec. Alexander Kerensky’s provisional government was overthrown in a “Revolution” named for this month, leading to the Russian Civil War. For ten points, name this autumn month which, in 1917, included the rise of Vladimir Lenin and Soviet Russia.",
      "answer": "October"
    },
    {
      "question": "While attending a sermon by this leader, reformer Michael Servetus was arrested and later burned at the stake. The Huguenots of France were Protestants who followed the doctrine of this reformer who served as de facto head of the Council of Geneva. This man attacked Roman Catholics and outlined his belief in “predestination” in the work Institutes of the Christian Religion. For ten points, name this Protestant reformer who fled France for Switzerland in 1536.",
      "answer": "John Calvin"
    },
    {
      "question": "This European ethnic group was discovered whaling off the coast of Newfoundland by French explorers during the 16th Century. The first circumnavigator of the world, Juan Sebastian Elcano, was a member of this group, as were the founders of the Jesuits, Francis Xavier and Ignatius of Loyola. A separatist group representing these people was falsely accused of the 2004 Madrid train bombings after having plotted similar attacks in Bilbao. For ten points, name these speakers of Euskara from Spain and France.",
      "answer": [
        "Basques",
        "Euskaldunak",
        "Vascos"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Konrad I, Duke of Mazovia, bequeathed land to this group in modern day Chelmno to ward off pagan raids. Alexander Nevsky’s victory in the Battle of the Ice, fought on a frozen Lake Peipus [[PAY-pus]], led to this group renouncing their claims on Russia. This order's supreme office was called a Hochmeister [[HOKE-mai-stehr]], and it lost much of its Baltic land after a Polish-Lithuanian force defeated it at Grunwald. For ten points, name this Catholic crusading order of German Knights.",
      "answer": [
        "Teutonic Knights or Order of Brothers of the German House of Saint Mary in Jerusalem",
        "Teutonic Order"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "English physician Thomas Sydenham wrote a 17th century manual advocating for a product containing this good, laudanum. Soldiers from the Kuomintang organized what became the \"Golden Triangle\" for production of this good while operating in Laos, Thailand and Myanmar. European traders sold this good to circumvent the Canton system, which exclusively required silver be spent to acquire goods like tea and porcelain. The Qing [[CHING]] and British empires fought two wars named for, for ten points, what illicit drug later used to produce heroin?",
      "answer": [
        "Opium poppy",
        "Opium Wars",
        "Opium Triangle",
        "or Opium Crescent"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The deflection of this element’s particles led to J. J. Thomson’s discovery of atomic isotopes. It’s not krypton, but British chemist Sir William Ramsay and Morris W. Travers isolated this element in 1898 and named it for the Greek word for “New.” As a byproduct of air liquefaction, this element was shown by Georges Claude to be able to produce light in sealed tubes. For ten points, name this element historically used for signs in Las Vegas.",
      "answer": [
        "Neon",
        "Ne before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The first engagement in this war began in Wallachia at the Battle of Oltenita. This war's Danubian phase ended when Omar Pasha defeated Prince Gorchakov at Silistria. In one battle in this war, only the ship Taif [[TAH-eef]] escaped an attack by Pavel Nakhimov at Sinope [[SIH-noh-pee]]. This war included battles at Malakoff redoubt and the Great Redan by French and British forces as part of the Siege of Sevastopol, an effort to capture the Tsar's Black Sea Fleet. For ten points, name this 1853 to 1856 war between Russia and an Ottoman- European coalition.",
      "answer": "Crimean War"
    },
    {
      "question": "This prime minister ordered British forces to bombard Alexandria in response to the 'Urabi [[oo-RAH-bee]] revolt. The Hawarden [[HAR-den]] Kite was an infamous news scoop that suggested this man supported Irish Home Rule. This leader attacked a prominent political rival over their response to the “Bulgarian Horrors” in his Midlothian campaign. For ten points, name this four-time Liberal British prime minister during the nineteenth century and rival of Benjamin Disraeli.",
      "answer": "William Ewart Gladstone"
    },
    {
      "question": "All three daughters of one ruler of this name were accused of adultery in the Tour de Nesle [NEH-luh]] Affair. One ruler of this name sent his son Louis to go on the Albigensian Crusade. That ruler with this name crushed the English at the Battle of Bouvines [[boo- VEEN]]. A Spanish ruler of this name invaded the Netherlands in the Eighty Years’ War, and that ruler of this name formed a fleet with the aim of deposing Elizabeth I that was defeated at Gravelines [[grav-LEEN]]. For ten points, give this name of the king who created the Spanish Armada.",
      "answer": [
        "Philip",
        "Philip IV",
        "Philip II of France",
        "Philip II of Spain",
        "Felipe",
        "Philippe in place of Philip"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "With his officers, this leader organized the Bayard Order to put on plays and patronize the arts. Voltaire revised this man's essay Anti-Machiavel, which was a scathing critique of cynicism in The Prince. This leader nearly ran away to England with his male lover, Hans Hermann von Katte, though he was caught and forced to watch Katte's execution by his father, Frederick William. For ten points, name this Crown Prince-turned-King of Prussia, who became famous for his military genius.",
      "answer": [
        "Frederick the Great or Friedrich der Große ]",
        "Frederick II",
        "or Friedrich II",
        "Old Fritz",
        "or Der Alte Fritz"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A program named for this color in Australia supposedly helped end gambling dens in Pakapoo, later ending after the passing of the Migration Act. The Vestal Virgins wore robes of this color, which nicknames a period of political repression by the Taiwanese Kuomintang from 1947 until the 1990s. Though they criticized a movement named for this color, the Black Hundreds were part of that movement with liberals and Kerenskyites in Russia. The Red Bolsheviks were opposed by a faction named for, for ten points, what color?",
      "answer": [
        "White",
        "the Whites",
        "White Terror"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Due to his father's exhausting work on calculating taxes, this scientist developed a working calculator at age nineteen, though it was primarily used as a toy for aristocrats. This man attacked casuistry [[KAZ-yoo-is-tree]] in a series of letters that were ordered to be burnt by King Louis XIV [[the Fourteenth]], and were eventually published as the Provincial Letters. Developing a notable \"Wager\" over the possibility of God's existence, for ten points, who was this French polymath of the early seventeenth century?",
      "answer": [
        "Blaise Pascal",
        "Pascal's Wager"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "19th century scholar Franz Mone [[MOH-nuh]] suggested the site of this battle was also the place where the hero of the Song of the Nibelung, Sigurd, slew the dragon Fafnir. Following this battle, a chieftain of the Cherusci [[keh-ROO-skee]] sent the head of his opponent to the Marcomanni to secure an alliance. At Kalkriese Hill, Germanic chieftain Arminius ambushed the forces of Varus, beginning this battle. Emperor Augustus cried \"Give me back my Legions\" following, for ten points, which devastating Roman defeat in the first century?",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of the Teutoburg Forest or die Schlacht im Teutoburger Wald",
        "prompt on the \"Varian Disaster\" before \"Varus\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Bernard de Montfaucon [[mont-foh-KOHN]] brought this artwork to the attention of of Europe when he hired Antoine Benoit [[beh-NWAH]] to copy it in its entirety. This artwork, which includes an early depiction of Halley's Comet, depicts Count Guy of Ponthieu [[pohn- TOO]] holding an English king captive for ransom. During the early days of the French Revolution, this artwork was seized by the Directory to be used to cover the tops of military wagons. Harold Godwinson is shown taking an arrow in the eye in, for ten points, which medieval \"Tapestry\" depicting the Battle of Hastings?",
      "answer": "Bayeaux ] Tapestry"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler personally met with Richard Cobden, convincing him to sign the Cobden- Chevalier [[sheh-vahl-YAY]] agreement, which sparked the \"golden age\" of free trade treaties. This ruler personally led the victorious army at the Battle of Magenta before directly defeating Franz Joseph I at the Battle of Solferino. Though he narrowly avoided war during the Luxembourg Crisis, this monarch openly wandered the battlefield before being captured by invading Germans at Sedan. For ten points, name this president-turned- emperor, the last monarch of France.",
      "answer": "Napoleon III or Charles Louis Napoléon Bonaparte"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's grandfather with a similar name was pardoned by Martin van Buren after his violation of the Neutrality Act during the 1837 Upper Canada revolt. Heavy losses in the Dieppe Raid led to this leader instituting a national draft, leading to the Conscription Crisis of 1944. This longest serving prime minister of one country formally asked George VI permission to declare war on Nazi Germany. The leader of World War Two-era Canada was, for ten points, which Liberal prime minister?",
      "answer": "William Lyon MacKenzie King"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this war, General Abebe Aregai [[ah-REH-guy]] failed to stop the \"March of the Iron Will\" by the mechanized columns of Pietro Badoglio. The League of Nations was discredited following the proposal of the Hoare-Laval Pact, which agreed Britain and France wouldn't intervene in this war. Revanchist tendencies caused by the 1896 Battle of Adwa led to Mussolini organizing this war to created a unified \"Italian East Africa.\" The deposition of Haile Selassie occurred as a result of, for ten points, what war which led to an African nation's occupation?",
      "answer": "Second Italo-Ethiopian War"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) Which Russian Tsar developed the repressive oprichnina state policing system and accidentally murdered his son during a dispute?",
      "answer": [
        "I",
        "v",
        "a",
        "n",
        "t",
        "h",
        "e",
        "r",
        "b",
        "l",
        "o",
        "G",
        "z",
        "y",
        ";",
        "c",
        "p",
        "s",
        "F",
        "m",
        "d"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The government that started this war was re-elected when Lord Salisbury triumphed in the\nKhaki Election. This war was ended by the Treaty of Vereeniging [vur-EEN-uh-ging]. The raid\nled by Leander Starr Jameson raised tensions before this war. It was sparked by the discovery of\ngold in the Witwatersrand [wit-wut-urz-and]. For 10 points, name this war in which Great Britain\ndefeated Dutch-speaking South African farmers.",
        "answer": [
          "Second Boer War",
          "Boer War"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The British used these facilities to house Boer civilians during the war, often with little\nfood. Later, worse examples include Buchenwald [boo-ken-vahld] and Dachau[dock-ow].",
        "answer": [
          "concentration camps",
          "prison camps",
          "internment camps"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Bernard of Saxe-Weimar led cavalry into French service during this war that included the Battle of Allerheim. The city of Magdeburg was sacked by General Tilly during this war, whose early “Danish” phase resulted from the disastrous folly of pro-Protestant King Christian IV. For 10 points, name this religious war in Germany that lasted from 1618 to 1648?",
        "answer": "Thirty Years' War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Thirty Years' War was ended by what peace accord signed at Munster and Osnabruck that is considered the foundation of the modern system of state sovereignty?",
        "answer": "Peace of Westphalia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Ivy Mike made use of this process, which is enabled by the Teller-Ulam design. Inertial confinement attempts to cause this reaction in a deuterium or tritium pellet. A Japanese fishing boat’s crew were affected by the Castle Bravo test of a weapon relying on this process. For 10 points, identify this joining together of atomic nuclei, used to power a hydrogen bomb.",
        "answer": "nuclear fusion"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What massive Russian fusion bomb’s 1961 test detonation created the largest human- caused explosion in history?",
        "answer": "Tsar Bomba"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader was sent to the Canary islands after the rise of the Popular Front and was a leader of the Foreign Legion during the Rif War. This leader is buried in the Valley of the Fallen, a monument which was built under his rule. This leader joined his Falange party to the Carlists. For 10 points, name this Fascist leader of Spain who won the Spanish Civil War.",
        "answer": "Francisco Franco"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Franco was supported in the Spanish Civil War by this air unit, which bombed Guernica. It was mainly composed of volunteers from Luftwaffe.",
        "answer": "Condor Legion"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler’s wedding was preceded by a failed assassination attempt against Gaspard de Coligny, and this ruler gained a decisive victory at the battle of Ivry over the Duke of Mayenne and the Catholic League. This ruler was assassinated by Francois Ravaillac, though he survived the St. Bartholomew’s Day massacre. After repeated failed sieges of Paris, he gained the throne by converting to Catholicism. For 10 points, name this victor of the War of the Three Henries, the first French king from the House of Bourbon.",
        "answer": "Henry IV of France"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Henry IV issued this edict granting religious tolerance to Huguenots in 1598. It was later overturned by the Edict of Fontainebleau.",
        "answer": "Edict of Nantes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this battle, the losing side briefly captured Fort Vaux. The winning side in this battle used rapid rotations, cycling in new troops to the front line every two weeks. Erich von Falkenhayn was removed as Chief of Staff after his failure to win this battle, though his goal of “bleeding France white” was met with over 300,000 French casualties. Phillippe P’etain ordered no retreat from, for ten points, what nine-month battle for a fortress complex in World War I?",
        "answer": "Battle of Verdun"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Falkenhayn was replaced by a pair of leaders: Erich Ludendorff and this officer, who appointed Hitler Chancellor of Germany in 1933 and is the namesake of a zeppelin that crashed in New Jersey in 1937.",
        "answer": "Paul von Hindenburg"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Max Hodel and Karl Nobiling attempted to assassinate one ruler from this house. Vincent, Count of Benedetti demanded that one prince of this house should reject offers to the Spanish throne, which were sensationalized in the Ems Dispatch. This house was overthrown in the November Revolution, leading to the establishment of the Weimar [VYE-mar] Republic. For ten points, name this German royal house that lost power after the abdication of Wilhelm II.",
        "answer": "House of Hohenzollern"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Ems Dispatch triggered this war in 1870. Napoleon III was captured at the Battle of Sedan during this war.",
        "answer": "Franco-Prussian War"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One side’s monarch in this war was captured at the Skirmish at Bender. Grengam and Gangut were two major naval battles in this war, in which Augustus the Strong was defeated. The Cossack leader Ivan Mazeppa switched sides in this war, which was ended by the Treaty of Nystad. One side attacked in a blinding snowstorm to win the Battle of Narva in this war, though Charles XII would later be defeated at Poltava by Peter the Great. For ten points, name this early 18th century war in which Russia soundly defeated Sweden.",
        "answer": "Great Northern War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Peter the Great overestimated Russian strength in the war when he turned and attacked this empire’s ports on the Black Sea.",
        "answer": "Ottoman Empire"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "With Rufus Isaacs, this man was accused of speculating on inside knowledge during the Marconi scandal of 1913. This man addressed the Shell Crisis during World War I as Minister of Munitions, and he succeeded Lord Kitchener as Secretary of State for War in 1916. This only Prime Minister to have spoken fluent Welsh was among the “Big Four” at the Versailles Conference. For ten points, name this Liberal British Prime Minister who presided over the end of World War I.",
        "answer": "David Lloyd George"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Italian member of the Big Four quarreled with his foreign minister, Sidney Sonnino, left the conference without signing.",
        "answer": "Vittorio Orlando"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event, Josefinas Hospital was destroyed by an incendiary bomb. This event was described for the London Times by George Steer. The aftermath of this event, which included eight separate waves progressing from heavy bombs, to machine gun strafing, to firebombs, was interpreted in a chaotic mural-sized artwork that shows a speared horse. For ten points, name this 1937 German bombing of a village during the Spanish Civil War, the subject of a large greyscale painting by Pablo Picasso.",
        "answer": "bombing of Guernica"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Guernica is a cultural center of this northern Spanish territory.",
        "answer": "Basque country"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Sayyid Qutb was arrested and executed for plotting to kill this man. This man’s anti-aircraft battery on Green Island was destroyed during the War of Attrition. This man, who outlined his ambitions in Philosophy of the Revolution, rose to power after deposing Farouk I as head of the Free Officers Movement. The Aswan High Dam was built by, for ten points, what predecessor of Anwar Sadat as President of Egypt?",
        "answer": "Gamel Abdel Nasser"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Nasser faced an invasion by French and British paratroopers after nationalizing this waterway.",
        "answer": "Suez Canal"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The last verse of the Italian national anthem refers to an eagle which “drank the blood of Italy and [this country’s] blood.” Louis XV backed his father in-law during a succession conflict in this country, which broke out after the death of King Augustus the Strong. This country was established by Mieszko I of the Piast Dynasty. Austria, Prussia and Russia partitioned this country three times. For ten points, name this country, once in a commonwealth with Lithuania, whose capital is Warsaw.",
        "answer": "Poland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The first elected King of the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth was Henry of this house. After the death of Charles IX, Henry returned to France to become Henry III, the last French king of this house.",
        "answer": [
          "House of Valois",
          "Henry III of Valois"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "As a child, this ruler was attacked by Tsuda Sanzo in the Otsu incident. This ruler’s forces attacked striking gold miners in the Lena massacre. A human stampede occurred during this ruler’s coronation at the Khodynka fields. The forces of this ruler violently cracked down on a demonstration led by Father Gapon, leading to Bloody Sunday. This ruler’s son Alexei’s hemophilia was allegedly cured by the “mad” monk Grigory Rasputin. For ten points, name this last Romanov tsar who was overthrown in the Russian Revolution.",
        "answer": "Nicholas II of Russia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the reign of Nicholas II, one of these events broke out in Kishinev in 1903. The majority of these events occurred in the Pale of Settlement.",
        "answer": "pogrom"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Pope Alexander II sent papal standards to the victor of this battle in an attempt to expand Catholic power. Many retreating troops from the losing side of this battle fell into the Evil Ditch, or the “Malfosse.” In this battle, which was preceded by an engagement at Fulford, the losing side’s huscarls could not prevent their king from being shot in the eye. The English formed a shield wall in this battle, fought three weeks after Harald Hardrada was killed at Stamford Bridge. For ten points, name this 1066 victory for William the Conqueror over Harold Godwinson.",
        "answer": "Battle of Hastings"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The heirless death of this English king, a son of Aethelred the Unready, led to the succession crisis that ended with William’s victory at Hastings.",
        "answer": "Edward the Confessor"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man, who tried Archbishop Aloysius Stepinac for collaborating with the Nazis, led the only Eastern European nation that accepted aid from the ECA. He defeated Chetnik leader Draa Mihailovic [mee-hail-oh-vitch] before reaching his highest office. This man’s country was kicked out of COMINFORM after his feud with Stalin led to a break with the USSR in 1949. For ten points, name this communist ruler of Yugoslavia and guerrilla leader during World War II.",
        "answer": "Josip Broz Tito"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Tito was the first Secretary General of this group, which Sukarno and Kwame Nkrumah helped found in 1961.",
        "answer": "Non-Aligned Movement or NAM"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler ceded territory to Safavid Persia in the Treaty of Resht and the Treaty of Ganja. This ruler’s reform of the church was implemented by Theophan Prokopovich. During the early years of his reign, this ruler reigned alongside his brother, Ivan V. This ruler won territory from Charles XII after signing the Treaty of Nystad at the end of the Great Northern War. The Battle of Poltava was won by forces under, for ten points, what westernizing Russian tsar who built a city once known as Leningrad?",
        "answer": "Peter the Great or Peter I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Peter undertook a Grand Embassy to the west, but returned prematurely to brutally address this 1698 uprising of these Russian armed guards.",
        "answer": "Streltsy Uprising or Revolt, etc."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event prevented a plebiscite proposed by Kurt Schuschnigg [shush-nig]. The Mauthausen-Gusen campwasestablishedshortlyafterthisevent, whichwasdeclarednullandvoidbytheMoscowDeclaration. This event was encouraged by Arthur Seyss-Inquart, and led to the resignation of President Wilhelm Miklas. This event established the province of Ostmark under the justification of lebensraum, and was followed by the annexation of the Sudetenland. For ten points, name this 1938 event in which Nazi Germany annexed Austria.",
        "answer": [
          "Anschluss",
          "Nazi annexation of Austria before 1938 is mentioned, prompting on partial answers"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A political union between Austria and Germany was explicitly forbidden by the Treaty of Versailles, signed by Germany, and this treaty, signed by German-Austria at the end of World War I.",
        "answer": "Treaty of St. Germain-en-Laye"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man supported the role of the Church by passing the Falloux [fall-ooh] Laws to reform schools. This ruler launched a failed coup at Strasbourg and was imprisoned in a fortress at Ham. This man, who was opposed by Adolphe Thiers in the National Assembly, sought to protect Constantinople by starting the Crimean War and was captured in 1870 at the Battle of Sedan during a disastrous defeat to Prussia. For ten points, name this final Emperor of France.",
        "answer": "Napoleon III"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Napoleon III supported an expedition to install this Austrian as Emperor of Mexico, but he failed to completely overthrow Benito Ju´arez and was executed in 1867.",
        "answer": "Maximilian I of Mexico"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The losing side in this battle lost the commander of its vanguard, Jean le Maingre [MAN-gruh]. The losers were able to successfully raid the baggage train of the victor of this battle, but lost their commander Charles d’Albret and were forced to sign the Treaty of Troyes. A cavalry charge during this battle was bogged down by mud and ran into stakes, leading to massive losses of knights. For ten points, name this decisive victory for English longbowmen during the Hundred Years’ War.",
        "answer": "Battle of Agincourt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another decisive victory for England in the Hundred Years War was this 1346 victory for Edward III, which allowed him to capture Calais and proved the importance of the longbow.",
        "answer": "Battle of Cr´ecy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader called a Congress of Berlin in order to override the Treaty of San Stefano. He supported Lord Derby’s attempts to pass a Reform Act prohibiting rotten boroughs. This leader’s foreign policies included buying out the Suez Canal Company and ordering a failed invasion of Afghanistan as part of the Great Game with Russia. This politician was a favorite of Queen Victoria and crowned her Empress of India. For ten points, name this Conservative prime minister of Great Britain and rival of William Gladstone.",
        "answer": "Benjamin Disraeli"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Disraeli began his political career as a supporter of this prominent Conservative, but eventually opposed him over his repeal of the Corn Laws. This man, who employed William Gladstone in his cabinet, created the first English police force.",
        "answer": "Sir Robert Peel"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While defending this government, Jaroslaw Dombrowski supposedly asked “do they still think me a traitor?” as he died. Gustave Courbet fled to Switzerland after advocating the destruction of the Vendˆome Column during this government’s tenure. Supporters of this government were shot at the Federalists’ Wall in P`ere Lachaise [pair la-shez] during the Bloody Week, in which Marshal MacMahon restored control for Adolphe Thiers [tee-air]. For ten points, name this revolutionary socialist government, formed after the Franco-Prussian War in the French capital.",
        "answer": "Paris Commune"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Adolphe Theirs was the first president of this French government, which lasted until France’s defeat in World War II.",
        "answer": "French Third Republic"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was threatened by a rival expedition led by Francisco de Garay. He invaded Honduras to defeat his rebellious lieutenant Crist´obal the Old. This man was attacked by his rivals Diego Velazquez and Bishop Fonseca in the Council of the Indies. This man burned his ships after landing at modern Veracruz and allied with the people of Tlaxcala [t’lahsh-kah-lah]. He captured Montezuma II in his capital of Tenochtitlan and created the Viceroyalty of New Spain. For ten points, name this conquistador who conquered the Aztec Empire.",
        "answer": "Hernan Cortes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Cortes implemented this system of forced labor in New Spain, where a number of natives were granted to conquistadors, who in return were supposed to protect them and convert them.",
        "answer": "encomienda"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man began his “New Course” by appointing Leo von Caprivi as chancellor. He flew into a rage during an interview with the Daily Telegraph and sent the gunboat Panther to start the Agadir Crisis. This man replaced Helmuth von Moltke the Younger with Erich von Falkenhayn after the failure of the Schlieffen Plan. This grandson of Victoria supported Austria after the death of Franz Ferdinand and dismissed Otto von Bismarck. For ten points, name this last Kaiser of Germany, who ruled during World War I.",
        "answer": "Wilhelm II or William II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Wilhelm II appointed this man Chief of the General Staff in the second half of World War I. He later served as president of the Weimar Republic.",
        "answer": "Paul von Hindenburg"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler abandoned his French allies by signing the Treaty of Breslau, exiting a conflict he later re-entered by invading Bohemia. This ruler’s father captured him in the act of fleeing to England, then forced him to watch the execution of his lover, Hans van Katte. This ruler connected his territory in the First Partition of Poland, and this builder of Sanssouci [san-soo-see] Palace started the War of the Austrian Succession by invading Silesia. For ten points, name this “Great” king of Prussia.",
        "answer": "Frederick the Great or Frederick II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Frederick allied himself in the Seven Years War with England against Russia, France, and Austria in this event, a reversal of traditional European alliances.",
        "answer": "Diplomatic Revolution"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader was beaten despite the actions of the king Prasutagus, who had betrothed his land to Claudius. The Ninth Legion was destroyed by this leader’s forces, along with the allied Trinovantes people. While Suetonius was away campaigning, this leader started a revolt by attacking the colony at Camulodunum. This leader’s defeat at the Battle of Watling Street came after her sack of Londinium. For ten points, name this queen who launched a major revolt in Roman Britain.",
        "answer": "Boudica or Boadicea"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Boudica and Prasutagus were rulers of this tribe in eastern Britain, near modern Suffolk.",
        "answer": "Iceni or Eceni"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man refused a promotion to a desk job by saying “every poor fellow in the trenches must do his duty.” Donald Cunnel is credited with inflicting a serious head wound on this man, who attempted to kill Wilfred May but was stopped by Arthur Brown. Propaganda about this man stated the British would automatically award a Victoria Cross to anyone that could kill him. The Flying Circus was led by, for ten points, what World War I German aviator commonly known by a colorful noble title?",
        "answer": [
          "Manfred Albrecht Freiherr von Richthofen",
          "the Red Baron"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the deaths of Richthofen and Wilhelm Reinhard, command of The Flying Circus was given to this man. During World War II, this Nazi was named Reichsmarschall and commanded the Luftwaffe.",
        "answer": "Hermann Wilhelm Goering"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle was preceded by a gift of sports balls to remind the winning king that he should stick to tennis. The fall of Harfleur prompted the losing side to fight this battle. At this battle, the order to kill all prisoners was given after Henry V feared that his baggage train would be overrun. This battle’s losing side could not use cavalry thanks to stakes placed in muddy ground; instead the winning side’s longbowmen fired at will. For ten points, name this 1415 battle fought on St. Crispin’s Day, a victory for England in the Hundred Years’ War.",
        "answer": "Battle of Agincourt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The English longbow also played a big role in this 1346 battle, where it prevailed over Genoese crossbows. Shortly after this battle, Calais [cah-lay] fell to England.",
        "answer": "Battle of Crecy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In an unfinished story from this collection, Canace finds a falcon who was abandoned by her lover and then shows a romantic interest in her brother, who is also Genghis Khan’s son. In this collection’s first story, Palamon and Arcite fight in a massive battle to win Emily’s hand in marraige. Characters in this work include the Squire and his father, the Knight, who tell stories during their pilgrimage to the shrine of Thomas Becket. For ten points, name this story collection by Geoffrey Chaucer.",
        "answer": "The Canterbury Tales"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Geoffrey Chaucer wrote The Canterbury Tales in this language, which was in use from approximately the Norman conquest of Britain through the 16th century.",
        "answer": "Middle English"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle’s winning commander allegedly declared “by tomorrow, I shall have gained a peerage or Westminster Abbey” before leading the Vanguard into combat. After this battle, Armand Blanquet [blan-kay] was sacked for surrendering the undamaged Franklin. Poorly stored paint caused an explosion aboard the L’Orient [lor-ee-ahn] in this battle, which was fought in Aboukir Bay. Napoleon’s expedition withdrew from North Africa shortly after losing, for ten points, what 1798 naval battle to Horatio Nelson in Egypt?",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of the Nile",
          "Battle of Aboukir Bay before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of the Nile was preceded by this land battle where Napoleon used squares to thwart Ottoman Mamluk cavalry. At this battle, Napoleon told his men that “40 centuries of history look down upon you.”",
        "answer": "Battle of the Pyramids"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler was denounced as illegitimate by Pope Pius V in the bull Regnans in Excelsis after refusing to persecute minority religions. The use of fireships at Gravelines [grah-vel-een] allowed this ruler to stave off enemy invasion. While preparing for an imminent attack from the Spanish Armada, this ruler inspired the troops at Tilbury by claiming to possess the “body of a weak, feeble woman” but the “heart and stomach of a king.” Anne Boleyn was the mother of, for ten points, what Virgin Queen of 16th century England?",
        "answer": "Elizabeth I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During Elizabeth’s fight against the Spanish Armada, she hired this privateer who attacked the Spanish fleet at Cadiz and later circumnavigated the globe for England.",
        "answer": "Sir Francis Drake"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, Charles Hay’s troops toasted his enemies and asked them to fire first; Maurice de Saxe prevailed over the Duke of Cumberland in that Battle of Fontenoy. Disagreements over whether Charles VI could violate Salic law in proclaiming his heir helped prompt this war, which began when Silesia was invaded by Frederick the Great of Prussia. For ten points, name this 1740 war over Maria Theresa’s succession to a Habsburg throne.",
        "answer": "War of the Austrian Succession"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Shortly after the War of the Austrian Succession, the alliances shifted in this event, triggered by statesman Anton von Kaunitz. As a result of this event, France allied with Austria and Britain allied with Prussia.",
        "answer": "Diplomatic Revolution"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At this battle’s conclusion, William Washington had his horse shot out from under him as he tried to pursue the enemy commander. This battle’s losing side was misled into fighting by a report of an imminent attack on Fort Ninety-Six. The winning side in this battle deployed three defensive lines by the Broad River and resisted multiple assaults by the British Legion, leading Daniel Morgan’s men to eventually rout Banastre Tarleton’s forces. For ten points, name this 1781 battle of the Carolinas campaign that was fought on cattle grazing ground.",
        "answer": "Battle of Cowpens"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the Carolinas Campaign, the British were more successful in this 1780 battle in which Charles Cornwallis defeated Horatio Gates. Baron Johann de Kalb was killed in this battle.",
        "answer": "Battle of Camden"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This nation achieved recognition in the Twelve Years’ Truce, which was eventually broken when this nation was attacked by the Duke of Olivares. The Council of Blood was set up to quell insurrections in this nation by the Duke of Alba, who had been deployed by Philip II. The Peace of Westphalia formally ended this nation’s Eighty Years’ War with Spain and granted it its independence. For ten points, name this Low Country whose independence struggle was led by the House of Orange.",
        "answer": "The Netherlands or Holland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The resistance against the Spanish was led by this stadtholder from the House of Orange. He financed the Sea Beggars to attack Spanish shipping, but was assassinated by Balthasar Gerard.",
        "answer": "William the Silent or William I"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, an imprisoned king rode across Europe in fifteen days to rejoin his troops, only to die a few years later at the siege of Frederiksten. In this war’s decisive battle, one side’s attempts to appoint Alexander Menshikov as head of the Cossacks led Ivan Mazepa to defect. The Treaty of Nystad ended this war, shortly after military reforms led to a great Russian victory at Poltava. For ten points, name this war in which Peter the Great prevailed over the Swedish Empire.",
        "answer": "Great Northern War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the Battle of Poltava, Charles XII of Sweden fled to the Ottoman Empire; the Russians were not happy, and waged this campaign from 1710 to 1711.",
        "answer": "Pruth River campaign"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man addressed deficiencies in message encrypting by adopting the new “Shark” system of communication. Otto Kranzbuhler successfully defended this man’s refusal to help survivors of the Laconia incident, leading him to only be jailed for ten years. After succeeding Erich Raeder in his highest post, this man launched Operation Drumbeat to begin the “Second Happy Time.” He advocated for wolf-pack tactics to win the battle of the Atlantic against allied shipping. For ten points, name this admiral of the Kriegsmarine for most of World War II.",
        "answer": "Karl Donitz"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the final days of World War II, Karl Donitz became the leader of this short-lived government. Based in a town in Northern Germany, it capitulated in three weeks to the Allies.",
        "answer": "Flensburg Government"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ethnic group was involved in the Bambatha Rebellion in 1907, and it won a major military victory in 1879 after a solar eclipse appeared over the battlefield. This ethnic group was defeated at the Battle of Blood River, and this ethnic group’s king, Cetshwayo, was defeated at the Battle of Rorke’s Drift. For ten points, name this ethnic group, the victors at the Battle of Isandlwana, who ruled an empire in southern Africa until they were conquered by the British.",
        "answer": "amaZulu people"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Zulu king revamped their military procedures and died in 1828, well before the British conquest.",
        "answer": "Shaka Zulu or Shaka kaSenzangakhona"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At a 1993 auction, a dummy named Ivan that was meant to test conditions prior to this man’s most famous undertaking sold for nearly $200,000. A cedar tree inspired the most famous callsign of this man, who exclaimed “Poyekhali!” In 1968, this man died while flying a MiG-15 after an air traffic controller misreported the weather, according to declassified files. After a mission of less than two hours in 1961, this man parachuted back to Earth. For ten points, name this cosmonaut who, aboard Vostok 1, became the first man in space.",
        "answer": "Yuri Alekseyevich Gagarin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1967, Gagarin was the backup pilot for the first manned flight of this Soviet spacecraft, which led to the first in-flight death in spaceflight history. This series of spacecraft is still in use by the Russian space program.",
        "answer": [
          "Soyuz",
          "Soyuz 1"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was forced to appoint the maligned Carlos Navarro as prime minister after Luis Carrero Blanco was assassinated in Operation Ogre. This leader rose to prominence fighting Abd el-Krim in the Rif War before taking part in a coup arranged by Emile Mola. In the civil war that followed, this man managed to unite the Carlists and the Falange, leading Nationalists to victory over the Republicans. For ten points, name this fascist leader of Spain.",
        "answer": "Francisco Franco Bahamonde"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Rif War was a Spanish attempt to quell an insurrection in this African country, where the Riffians were essentially an independent people living in a Spanish protectorate.",
        "answer": "Morocco"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Canadian hundred dollar bill depicts a woman observing this compound through a microscope. A scientist remarked that it had gotten “the disulphides right” upon seeing Dorothy Hodgkin’s X-ray crystallographic structure of this compound, which helped him confirm the chemical structure of this compound’s A and B chains. After blocking off pancreatic ducts in dogs, Charles Best and Frederick Banting used extracts containing this compound to reduce blood sugar. For ten points, name this protein hormone that is used to treat diabetes.",
        "answer": "insulin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This British biochemist first sequenced insulin. Dideoxynucleotides [di-dee-oxy-nucleo-tides] are used to generate DNA fragments in this man’s namesake method of sequencing DNA.",
        "answer": "Frederick Sanger"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "C´ecile Renault was executed for being caught meeting this man while carrying knives. After the fall of this man, the Muscadins led the First White Terror to eliminate his supporters. This man created a holiday, held on the anniversary of the Champ de Mars Massacre, for his Cult of the Supreme Being. This man’s death led to the Thermidorean Reaction, and he was a member of the Committee of Public Safety alongside ally Louis St. Just. For ten points, name this Jacobin leader who led the Reign of Terror until he, too, was guillotined.",
        "answer": "Maximillian Robespierre"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Robespierre’s Cult of the Supreme Being was meant to replace this first atheistic French state religion. This deistic Cult shares its name with an Age written about by Thomas Paine.",
        "answer": [
          "Cult of Reason",
          "The Age of Reason"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler’s forces were victorious at the Battle of Shipka Pass, securing the Treaty of San Stefano and the liberation of Bulgaria from the Ottomans. The zemstvo system of local government was created during this ruler’s reign, which also included the sale of Alaska to the United States. This man was assassinated in St. Petersburg when a bomb was thrown into his carriage by the People’s Will. For ten points, name this Russian tsar who freed the serfs.",
        "answer": "Alexander II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1866, Alexander’s survival of an attack in St. Petersburg was commemorated by Viktor Hartmann, who sketched a “Great Gate” to be built in Kiev. While the gate was never built, the sketch inspired part of this Russian composer’s Pictures at an Exhibition.",
        "answer": "Modest Mussorgsky"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "ThismanlostcredibilityduringtheDailyTelegraphaffair,inwhichhewascriticizedfordescribingthe English as “mad as March hares.” This man controversially ordered his troops to fight so that “no Chinese will ever again dare to look cross-eyed” at them during the Boxer Rebellion. During the July Crisis, this man sent a series of telegraphs to his cousin, Nicholas II, in an attempt to avoid the mobilization of their armies. For ten points, name this German Kaiser who ruled during World War I.",
        "answer": [
          "Wilhelm II",
          "William II,"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the July Crisis, Wilhelm was advised by this general, the head of the German Army. This man’s uncle was made a field marshal after his success in the Franco-Prussian War.",
        "answer": "Helmuth von Moltke the Younger"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A king with this name codified maritime law in the Book of the Consulate of the Sea and conquered Majorca from the Muslims. Walter Stewart conspired to kill a king of this name, and another king with this name took power after the Battle of Sauchieburn but lost the Battle of Flodden. The Glorious Revolution replaced a king of this name with William III. A king with this name faced the Gunpowder Plot and united the thrones of England and Scotland. For ten points, Queen Elizabeth I was succeeded by a king with what name?",
        "answer": [
          "James accept, but do not reveal, James I of Aragon",
          "James I of Scotland after “Walter”",
          "acceptJamesIVofScotlandafter“Sauchieburn”",
          "acceptJamesIIofEnglandafter“Glorious”",
          "James I of England after “Gunpowder”"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Consulate of the Sea was established in the 13th century in this Spanish kingdom under the rule of its James I. Later rulers of this monarchy included Ferdinand II, husband of Isabella of Castile.",
        "answer": "Aragon"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle began when one side took a stand a Mozhaysk, refusing to follow Barclay de Tolly’s advice to retreat. Utitsa village was burned to the ground after it exchanged hands multiple times in this battle. The losing side in this battle sought to defend the Raevsky redoubt. After defeating Mikhail Kutuzov, this battle’s victors entered Moscow, only to find it empty. For ten points, name this 1812 victory for Napoleon on Russian soil.",
        "answer": "Battle of Borodino"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This fictional man observes, then participates in, the Battle of Borodino in an 1869 novel. This character later decides to try to assassinate Napoleon and later marries Natasha Rostova.",
        "answer": [
          "Pierre Bezhukov",
          "either",
          "both names"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A refusal to recognize this country was maintained in the Hallstein Doctrine until the Basic Treaty normalized relations. The Monday Demonstrations led to the downfall of one of this country’s leaders. Its leaders included Egon Krenz, Erich Honecker, and Walter Ulbricht, and its secret police under Marcus Wolf closely collaborated with the KGB. For ten points, name this country that constructed the Berlin Wall to bar migration to its western neighbor.",
        "answer": [
          "East Germany or the German Democratic Republic",
          "Deutsche Demokratische Republik"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The division and administration of Germany after World War II was determined in August 1945 at a meeting in this city.",
        "answer": "Potsdam"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At the Battle of Cap Bon, this group killed over 10,000 Roman soldiers. These people’s king Godigisel died while this group crossed the Rhine River with the Alans and the Suebi. This Germanic tribe fought Belisarius at the Battle of Ad Decimum and Tricamarum near their capital of Carthage. The Hasdingi and Silingi formed this group, which invaded Iberia before conquering North Africa. For ten points, name these Germanic people whose name sounds like a criminal that destroys property.",
        "answer": "Vandals"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This last Germanic ruler of the Vandals deposed Hilderic and twice fled after facing off against Belisarius at Ad Decimum and Tricamarum.",
        "answer": "Gelimer"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man captured the cloth industry of Lille after a decisive victory at Mons-en-Pevele. This man carried out a burning at the stake on an island in the Seine to curb the influence of the Knights Templar, though his conquest of Flanders was set back at the Battle of the Golden Spurs. The Babylonian Captivity began when this man feuded with Pope Boniface VIII, forcing the papacy to move to Avignon. For ten points, name this French monarch who was named for his good looks.",
        "answer": [
          "Philip IV",
          "Philip the Fair"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Philip IV ordered the execution of this last Grand Master of the Knights Templar in 1314. The Freemasonry movement traces its connection to the Knights Templar to a secret act by this man.",
        "answer": "Jacques de Molay"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the wake of this event, Denis Berezovsky served one day as head of his country’s navy, then defected. Ilya Ponomarev was exiled shortly after he became the only representative of his country’s lower house to vote against this action, which critics claimed was a violation of the Budapest Memorandum. The Federal Assembly ratified a Treaty of Accession that officially approved this action, which followed the Euromaidan protest movement. “Little Green Men” helped carry out this action. The War in Donbass largely resulted from, for ten points, what action in which Vladimir Putin invaded an eastern European peninsula in 2014?",
        "answer": "Russian annexation of the Crimea"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Among the various international laws that deemed Russia’s annexation illegal was this set of accords, signed in Belarus in 1991, that established the CIS and declared the USSR no longer existant.",
        "answer": "Belavezha Accords"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these facilities in Sobibor was demolished after Alexander Pechersky and Leon Feldhendler organized a revolt. Methods developed in the Aktion T4 program were used in these facilities. Operation Reinhard involved the construction and use of these facilities, where Zyklon B was used; the operation was named for Reinhard Heydrich. Treblinka, Buchenwald, and Auschwitz were sites of, for ten points, what facilities built by Nazi Germany to carry out the Holocaust?",
        "answer": [
          "Nazi German extermination camps",
          "concentration camps",
          "equivalents like death camps"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The poison gas involved in Zyklon B is based on this compound, which was first isolated from the pigment Prussian blue.",
        "answer": [
          "cyanide",
          "hydrogen cyanide"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At this location, the Marquis de Lafayette’s willingness to kiss a queen’s hand helped calm tensions during the October Days after cannons from the Hotel de Ville were dragged here by angry women protesting the price of bread. Charles Le Brun helped supervise the construction of this facility, which featured gardens designed by Andre Le Notre and a Hall of Mirrors. Paris was replaced as the site of the royal court by, for ten points, what French palace complex built by Louis XIV [14]?",
        "answer": "Palace of Versailles"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Women’s March on Versailles, or the October Days, was a food riot of this social class. Over 90% of France was part of this class; the clergy and nobility held power as the two other classes.",
        "answer": "Third Estate"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This woman’s daughter Alix married Theobald the Good, who had attempted to abduct this woman herself for marriage. This woman allegedly chose the gravesite of Mary Magdalene as her departing point during the Second Crusade. This woman annulled her marriage to Louis VII before marrying a king who imprisoned her for 16 years following a failed revolt that she planned with her sons John and Richard the Lionheart. For ten points, name this 12th century queen consort of England, a noblewoman from Aquitaine.",
        "answer": "Eleanor of Aquitaine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Eleanor and Henry married in the cathedral of this French city, where Eleanor was probably born and where she legendarily developed a “Court of Love” to teach chivalry.",
        "answer": "Poitiers"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Cecile Renault attempted to assassinate this man and smiled at her execution. This man’s downfall came after Joseph Fouch´e managed to rally support against the Law of 22 Prairial. This man, who attempted to create a Deist religion known as the Cult of the Supreme Being, was called the “incorruptible.” The Thermidorian Reaction against this man ended with his beheading. For ten points, name this leader of the Committee of Public Safety during the Reign of Terror in the French Revolution.",
        "answer": "Maximilien Robespierre"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Robespierre’s Cult of the Supreme Being was meant to replace an atheistic “Cult of” this enlightenment concept that was promoted by people like Jacques H´ebert.",
        "answer": "Cult of Reason"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This monarch offered refuge to the exiled Duke of Warwick and arranged an alliance between the Duke and Margaret of Anjou. In the Treaty of Picquigny, this ruler paid 75,000 crowns to end the Hundred Years’ War. The League of the Public Weal was organized by the Duke of Berry to oppose this monarch. The death of this king’s rival, Charles the Bold, allowed him to annex Burgundy. For ten points, name this French king from 1461 to 1483 whose nickname is derived from his webs of schemes.",
        "answer": [
          "Louis XI",
          "Louis the Universal Spider"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Treaty of Picquigny was agreed to by Louis XI and this English king, the older brother of Richard III.",
        "answer": "Edward IV"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Harry von Arnim saw this man as a rival and thus stole sensitive records from an embassy in France. This man, whose policies included a Sickness Insurance Law and Accident Insurance Law, formed the League of the Three Emperors. This man helped provoke France into war with the Ems Dispatch and launched the Kulturkampf against Catholic power. This user of Realpolitik gave the “iron and blood” speech to the Prussian Chamber of Deputies. For ten points, name this first Chancellor of a unified Germany.",
        "answer": "Otto von Bismarck"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bismarck’s Kulturkampf was carried out through the May Laws, which were written by, and alternatively named for, this education minister.",
        "answer": [
          "Adalbert Falk",
          "Falk Laws"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A Russian memorial at this battle also commemorates Santarosa. Frank Abney Hastings led a night raid during this battle, in which the Scipion came under heavy attack. Bonfires were lit on Mount Parnassos after this battle, which was described by George IV as an “untoward event.” Henri de Rigny and Edward Codrington led the winning forces at this battle, which took place at Sphacteria inlet near Pylos. For ten points, name this 1827 battle, an Ottoman loss during the Greek War of Independence, that was the last battle between wooden ships.",
        "answer": "Battle of Navarino"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This son of Muhammad Ali ordered Codrington’s allied fleet to leave Navarino Bay; Codrington warned that they had come peacefully but would destroy this man’s fleet if they attacked. That happened.",
        "answer": "Ibrahim Pasha"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Samuel Nicholas is often considered the first leader of these people. In 1805, Presley O’Bannon received a Mameluke sword, which these people continue to ceremonially wear; O’Bannon led these people at the Battle of Derna, the first American battle on foreign soil. The service of these troops in the Barbary Wars inspired the line “to the shores of Tripoli” in their namesake hymn. A 1798 to 1800 conflict with France contributed to the creation of the US Navy and, for ten points, what other branch of the Armed Forces that carries out amphibious operations?",
        "answer": "US Marine Corps"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Samuel Nicholas led 200 Marines in the 1776 Battle of Nassau to recapture supplies that this British governor of Virginia had evacuated to the Bahamas. In 1775, this man offered freedom to any slaves willing to fight on the British side.",
        "answer": [
          "John Murray, 4th Earl of Dunmore",
          "Lord Dunmore"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The division of this man’s empire between his sons alk-Amin and al-Ma’mun caused a civil war. Before becoming a ruler, this man led an assault against Empress Irene, reaching as far as Chrysopolis before turning around. Twelve mechanical knights were part of a water clock that this man sent to Charlemagne with an elephant and other gifts. This man, whose epithet means “Rightly Guided,” created the House of Wisdom in Baghdad, which became a center of learning during the Islamic Golden Age. For ten points, name this fifth Abbasid Caliph.",
        "answer": "Harun al-Rashid BONUS:AmongthescholarswhoworkedintheHouseofWisdomwasthisastronomerandmathematician whose Compendious Book on Calculation by Completion inspired the name of, and revolutionized, algebra. ANSWER: Muhammmad ibn Musa al-Khwarizmi 2 This leader’s reputation was hurt after attempting to cover up a leak of the military exercise Fallex 62. This leader declared “this is our breakthrough” after a new plan to pool coal production with France was adopted in the Schuman Declaration. More controversially, this politician ordered the arrest of Der Spiegel journalists in 1962 after they had leaked state secrets. Ludwig Erhard’s post-war economic revitalization took place under, for ten points, what first Chancellor of West Germany? ANSWER: Konrad Adenauer"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Adenauer promoted this doctrine of refusing to hold diplomatic relations with countries that recognized East Germany. This doctrine was followed between 1955 and 1970.",
        "answer": "Hallstein Doctrine"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A Hanging Order was issued against this group after they led an uprising in the Penza area. “Temporary emergency measures” were used to justify the targeting of this group, which arose in the aftermathoftheStolypinreforms.Inthe1910s,thesepeoplewerelabeledas“bloodsuckers[and]vampires” for failing to give up their grain to the government of Vladimir Lenin. Joseph Stalin’s collectivization reforms targeted, for ten points, what class of wealthy Russian peasants?",
        "answer": "kulaks"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Kulak land was collectivized into Sovkhoz, or state-owned farms where workers were paid salaries, and into these jointly-owned community farms, where workers received profit sharing after selling its product to the state.",
        "answer": "kolkhozes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1305, a queen of Navarre with this first name supposedly died from witchcraft performed by the Bishop of Troyes [[TWAH]]. Many historical female aristocrats held this name, including \"of Lancaster\" and \"of the Tower.\" A Medieval chronicle written by Jean de Mailly [[mai-YEE]] tells of a female Pope by this name, now widely considered to be fictional. For ten points, give this name commonly associated with a French warrior saint who broke the English and Burgundian siege of Orléans during the Hundred Years' War.",
        "answer": [
          "Joan",
          "Joan I of Navarre",
          "Joan of Lancaster",
          "Joan of the Tower",
          "Pope Joan",
          "Joan of Arc"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Joan of Lancaster, a great-granddaughter of Louis VIII of France and Henry III of England, was a member of the House of Lancaster, a cadet branch of this royal house alongside the House of York.",
        "answer": "Plantagenet"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event, Gail Halvorsen popularized the mass distribution of candy to children in Operation Little Vittles. SPD party member Ernst Reuter gave a speech beside the ruined Reichstag urging the people of America, England, and France to not abandon his city during this event. At the height of this event, an Allied aircraft reached its target with supplies every thirty seconds. For ten points, name this event in which the Soviets attempted to stop supply lines to the West German capital, the first major crisis of the Cold War.",
        "answer": [
          "Berlin Blockade",
          "Berlin Airlift",
          "or Berliner Luftbrücke"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The catalyst for the Berlin Blockade was the Allied introduction of this new currency, the replacement for the similarly named Reichsmark, to the Soviet sector of Berlin.",
        "answer": "Deutsche Mark"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "When first observed, this substance was called \"dephlogisticated muriatic acid air\" by its discoverer, Carl Wilhelm Scheele [[SHAY-luh]]. John Davy exposed a mixture of this substance and carbon monoxide to sunlight, creating phosgene. This substance was first weaponized by Fritz Haber [[HAH-buhr]] and was deployed at the Second Battle of Ypres [[EE-pruh]]. Before Zyklon B, this substance was widely used as a chemical weapon in the 1910s to target Allied trenches. For ten points, name this toxic gas used by the Germans during World War One.",
        "answer": "Chlorine gas or Bertholite"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other substance was also developed as a chemical weapon for the German army during World War One. This substance is often misleadingly called a gas and causes blisters to the lungs and skin.",
        "answer": [
          "Mustard gas",
          "Sulfur Mustard 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 6"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler was given a large diamond from Golconda, India, called the Orlov. A favorite of this ruler joined the Familia faction to rebel against Augustus III and faced the Partition Sejm [[SAME]] and failed to protect the existence of Poland. Besides King Stanisław Poniatowski, this ruler was also courted by Ivan Rimsky-Korsakov and a man who died negotiating the Treaty of Jassy with the Ottomans. That lover, a Prince of Taurida, built namesake staged villages in the Crimea called Potemkin Villages. For ten points, name this Russian Tsarina.",
        "answer": [
          "Catherine the Great",
          "Catherine II"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Catherine the Great put down a 1770s rebellion of Cossacks led by this man who was imprisoned in a metal cage by Alexander Suvorov.",
        "answer": [
          "Yemelyan Pugachev",
          "Pugachev's Rebellion"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event, eleven detainees at a colonial detention camp were clubbed to death by guards in the Hola Massacre. In 1952, Governor Evelyn [[EEV-lin]] Baring declared a state of emergency and ordered the imprisonment of Jomo Kenyatta and other rebel leaders in an attempt to prevent this event from occurring. Dedan Kimathi was executed in 1957 after leading an army during this event. For ten points, name this event, an armed struggle between the Kenya Land and Freedom Army and the British authorities.",
        "answer": [
          "Mau Mau Uprising",
          "\"Rebellion\"",
          "\"Revolt\" in place of \"Uprising\"",
          "Kenya Emergency before \"Kenyatta\""
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1952, this future dictator of Uganda deployed to Kenya with the King's African Rifles and was later considered to be \"intensely loyal\" to Britain.",
        "answer": "Idi Amin Dada"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While leading military forces during this conflict, General Raoul Salan attempted a putsch staged from Corsica with support from Governor General Jacques Soustelle. The new Fifth Republic managed to negotiate the Évian Accords, ending this conflict and allowing France to retain the naval base at Mers El Kébir. The end of this war resulted in the mass emigration of Pied-Noirs [[PYAY-NWAHR]] to mainland France. For ten points, name this war between France and the National Liberation Front.",
        "answer": [
          "Algerian War of Independence or Algerian Revolution",
          "or War of 1 November"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This series of attacks by the FLN against targets across French Algeria on the first of November is considered the beginning of the Algerian War and translates into English as \"Red All Saints' Day.\"",
        "answer": "Toussaint Rouge"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A woman who stalked this man, Princess Catherine Radziwill, wrote a pamphlet defending his character titled The Resurrection of Peter. This man, who orchestrated the Jameson Raid, led the defense of Kimberly during the Second Boer War. A Punch Magazine cartoon depicted this figure as a Colossus with his two feet on Cape Town and Cairo, referencing a railway he hoped to build. For ten points, name this founder of the De Beers Diamond Company who names a scholarship which gives students a full ride to the University of Oxford.",
        "answer": "Cecil John Rhodes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Under Rhodes, the British South Africa Company defeated Lobengula in the First Matabele War, which took place in what is now this country. Its other ethnic groups include the Shona.",
        "answer": "Republic of Zimbabwe"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's last finished novel features William Pitt Ferrars, whose sister is a companion to Adrian Neuchatel, titled Endymion [[en-DIM-ee-on]]. This man ordered Robert Napier to invade Ethiopia. This man also enacted the Public Health Act and introduced competitive exams for Civil Servants. Politically, this man traded power with William Gladstone. A favorite of Queen Victoria, for ten points, who was this Conservative politician, the only Jewish British prime minister?",
        "answer": "Benjamin Disraeli"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another British politician with a Jewish heritage was this well-known classical economist who was born to Sephardic Jews of Portuguese origin, converted to Unitarianism in 1793, and bought a seat in Parliament for the Irish borough of Portarlington.",
        "answer": "David Ricardo"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An unswept chimney led to a destructive 1837 fire at this site, which occurred while the Imperial court was at Mikhailovsky Theatre. A Sergei Eisenstein film culminated in the storming of this structure by the Red Guard in 1917. Father Georgy Gapon led over 50 thousand demonstrators outside this site to protest autocracy, leading to hundreds dying from Imperial fire in the Bloody Sunday Massacre. For ten points, name this Imperial residence in Saint Petersburg, built by Peter the Great.",
        "answer": "Winter Palace or Zimnij dvorets"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "From February to October 1917, the Winter Palace served as the seat of the Russian Provisional Government led by this man before it was overthrown by the Bolsheviks.",
        "answer": "Alexander Kerensky 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 9"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Working with General David Canaberro, this general established the Juliana Republic in southern Brazil. This man was infuriated by an agreement made at Plombières [[plohm- BEE-air]], which promised to cede his home city of Nice to France. This leader of the \"Hunters of the Alps\" aligned with the Colorados during the Uruguayan Civil War, after which he returned to his home country to lead the Expedition of the Thousand to Sicily. For ten points, name this Italian general, considered a father of the First Italian Republic.",
        "answer": "Giuseppe Garibaldi or Giuseppe Maria Garibaldi"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which Italian statesman, who reluctantly negotiated the cessation of Savoy to France in the Treaty of Plombières, became the first prime minister of Italy?",
        "answer": [
          "Camillo Benso, Count of Cavour",
          "either underlined answer",
          "Camillo Paolo Filippo Giulio Benso, Count of Cavour, Isolabella and Leri"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During the first Easter festivities celebrated on Cebu [[SEE-boo]], this European formed a blood compact with the local tribal head, Rajah Humabon. Legendarily, Chief Lapu- Lapu slew this man with a traditional bolo knife during the Battle of Mactan. This man, who sailed under the Spanish flag, named the Pacific Ocean in the 1520s while leading an expedition to the East Indies. For ten points, name this Portuguese explorer whose crew completed the first circumnavigation of the globe.",
        "answer": [
          "Ferdinand Magellan",
          "Fernão de Magalhães",
          "or Fernando de Magallanes"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Lapu-Lapu was a chieftain of Mactan, in the Visayas group of which East Asian archipelago which was controlled by the Spanish until 1898?",
        "answer": [
          "Philippines",
          "Filipinas",
          "or Pilipinas",
          "Philippine Islands",
          "Archipelago"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Through the Riverdale Agreement, this specific group integrated their Dominion counterparts in Canada, Australia, and New Zealand. Utilizing the bouncing bomb, a squadron of this military force known as the \"Dam Busters\" caused a flood in the Ruhr valley during Operation Chastise. In reference to this specific military force, Winston Churchill stated \"Never in the field of human conflict was so much owed by so many to so few\" following their clash with the Luftwaffe in the Battle of Britain. For ten points, name this air force of Britain during the Second World War and beyond.",
        "answer": [
          "Royal Air Force",
          "RAF"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The RAF victory in the Battle of Britain prevented what Nazi invasion operation codenamed for an aquatic mammal?",
        "answer": [
          "Operation Sea Lion",
          "Unternehmen Seelöwe"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Due to the Treaty of Tolentino, this institution housed the Statue of the Tiber River with Romulus and Remus until the Hundred Days period of 1815. The Communards set fire to the adjoining Tuileries Palace, which spread and destroyed this palace's modern-day Richelieu [[ree-shah-LOO]] wing. A former employee of this institution, Vincenzo Peruggia, successfully hid the Mona Lisa and attempted to \"return it to its homeland.\" Originally built by Philip II Augustus, for ten points, what is this French palace and museum?",
        "answer": [
          "Louvre Museum or Musée du Louvre",
          "Louvre Palace",
          "or Palais du Louvre"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Grand Louvre revitalization project was encouraged by which socialist French president of the late 20th century, the architect of the Maastricht Treaty with German chancellor Helmut Kohl?",
        "answer": "Francois Mitterand or François Marie Adrien Maurice Mitterrand"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The 1st Earl of Shaftesbury likely manufactured charges of Catholic sympathies against this Admiralty Secretary, leading to his imprisonment in the Tower of London. This man, who was a member of the entourage of Charles II on his return from the Netherlands during the Restoration, recorded the destruction of St. Paul's Cathedral during a blaze which began on Pudding Lane. The 17th century Great Plague and Great Fire of London were chronicled by, for ten points, which former minister of Parliament who kept a diary that was published to popular acclaim in the 19th century?",
        "answer": "Samuel Pepys ]"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Pepys recorded his participation in the navy during which war's Raid of the Medway? England attempted to end a namesake rival's naval domination in the North Sea and English Channel in this war.",
        "answer": "Second Anglo-Dutch War"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, Sébastien Rale [[RAH-leh]] had a price put on his head by Massachusetts governor Joseph Dudley, who wrongly assumed he had led a raid in Maine. The expulsion of residents who were later dubbed \"Cajuns\" occurred during this war's American theater, known as \"Queen Anne's War.\" The death of the childless Charles II, a member of the Habsburg family, led to this multi-continental war. The Treaty of Utrecht ended, for ten points, what early 18th century war which led to the rise of the Bourbon monarchy in Iberia?",
        "answer": [
          "War of the Spanish Succession",
          "Queen Anne's War before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the European theatre of the war, the Duke of Marlborough was partnered with which French-born Austrian general who secured a major victory in the Siege of Turin?",
        "answer": "Eugene of Savoy or Prince Eugene Francis of Savoy–Carignano"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This writer theorized that Marx failed to consider the crucial role of non-capitalist economies in sustaining the rate of profit in her 1913 economics treatise The Accumulation of Capital. Karl Vogel was likely the soldier who shot this woman and threw her body into the Landwehr Canal following chancellor Friedrich Ebert's authorization of the Freikorps to suppress her movement. For ten points, name this German Communist who was executed during the defeat of the Spartacist uprising in January 1919.",
        "answer": "Rosa Luxemburg"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Luxemburg and her frequent collaborator Karl Liebknecht [[LEEB-nekt]] were both members of this German political party, which they left for the Communist Party after this party openly supported the German war effort during World War One.",
        "answer": [
          "Social Democratic Party of Germany or Sozialdemokratische Partei Deutschlands",
          "SPD"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this scandal, women such as Madame de Montespan [[mohn-teh-SPAHN]] and Olympia Mancini were accused of using the euphemistically named \"inheritance powders.\" The informant Marie Bosse led police chief Nicholas de la Reynie to the person believed to be at the heart of this scandal, La Voisin [[vwah-SAHN]], or \"the neighbor.\" For ten points, name this scandal which culminated in 1682 and involved many French nobles being executed at the \"Burning Court\" for administering toxic substances to wealthy relatives.",
        "answer": "The Affair of the Poisons or L'affaire des poisons"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Almost exactly a century later, the French court was again scandalized by an affair named for this item, which was acquired by the Comtesse de la Motte using Marie Antoinette's forged signature.",
        "answer": [
          "Affair of the Diamond Necklace",
          "Affair of the Queen's Necklace",
          "or Affaire du collier de la reine",
          "or collier de diamants"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "CUBA IN THE 19TH CENTURY",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The Spanish administrative capital, still the capital of modern Cuba?",
          "answer": "Havana"
        },
        {
          "question": "Song inspired by Jose Marti [mar-TEE] that became the most famous patriotic song of Cuba?",
          "answer": "Guantanamera"
        },
        {
          "question": "The main crop of Cuba, whose workers were organized into a revolution by Carlos Cespedes\n[SESS-pay-dace] and which is used to make rum?",
          "answer": [
            "sugar",
            "sugarcane",
            "sugar cane"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The knife-like weapons with a Spanish name used by revolutionaries under Carlos Cespedes?",
          "answer": "machetes"
        },
        {
          "question": "The manifesto written by Pierre Soule [soo-LAY] that declared that the U.S. should acquire\nCuba?",
          "answer": [
            "Ostend Manifesto",
            "Ostend"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The war begun by Carlos Cespedes, named after a period of time?",
          "answer": [
            "the Ten Years War",
            "Ten Years",
            "la Guerra de los Diez Anos",
            "Diez Anos",
            "la Guerra Grande"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The Spanish general nicknamed “the Butcher” for his brutality?",
          "answer": [
            "Valeriano Weyler",
            "Weyler"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The U.S. ship sending weapons to Cuba that was seized, leading to a namesake affair?",
          "answer": [
            "Virginius",
            "Virginius Affair"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Who or what was..."
    },
    {
      "category": "D-DAY",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The region of France that contains all five invasion beaches?",
          "answer": [
            "Normandy",
            "Normandie",
            "Lower Normandy"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The operational code name of D-Day?",
          "answer": [
            "Operation Overlord",
            "Overlord",
            "Operation Neptune",
            "Neptune"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The most heavily defended beach on D-Day, named after the largest city in Nebraska?",
          "answer": [
            "Omaha Beach",
            "Omaha"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The general, nicknamed “Desert Fox”, who commanded German forces at D-Day?",
          "answer": [
            "Erwin Rommel",
            "Rommel"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Oceanic term for the “wall” of German defenses along the French coast?",
          "answer": [
            "Atlantic Wall",
            "Atlantikwall"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The British namesake of modified tanks known as “funnies” used during the invasion?",
          "answer": [
            "Percy Cleghorn Hobart",
            "Hobart",
            "Percy Hobart"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The US Army division nicknamed the “Screaming Eagles” who paradropped behind German\nlines on D-Day?",
          "answer": [
            "101st Airborne",
            "101"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City on the Orne River that was liberated by the Canadians on July 9th, more than a month\nbehind schedule?",
          "answer": "Caen"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Before, during, and after D-Day, who or what was…"
    },
    {
      "category": "WAR OF THE SPANISH SUCCESSION",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the “Sun King” of France?",
          "answer": [
            "Louis XIV",
            "Louis the Great"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the royal house which the French wanted on the Spanish throne?",
          "answer": "Bourbon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the royal house which previously ruled Spain and also ruled Austria?",
          "answer": [
            "Habsburg",
            "Hapsburgs"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the king of Spain who died at the onset of the war, causing the succession crisis?",
          "answer": [
            "Charles II",
            "Carlos II"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the English king during the war, a Dutch stadtholder who jointly ruled with Mary?",
          "answer": [
            "William III of England",
            "William III",
            "William III of Orange",
            "William III of Scotland"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the preeminent English general of the war and ancestor of a later Prime Minister?",
          "answer": [
            "Duke of Marlborough",
            "Marlborough",
            "John Churchill",
            "Churchill",
            "First Duke of Marlborough",
            "Prince of Mindelheim",
            "Prince of Mellenburg"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the 1704 British victory that names a palace in Oxfordshire?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Blenheim",
            "Blenheim",
            "Blenheim Palace",
            "Battle of Blenheim Palace"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the French nobleman who took the Spanish throne at the beginning of the war?",
          "answer": [
            "Philip V",
            "Felipe V"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "During the War of Spanish Succession who or what…"
    },
    {
      "category": "FRENCH REVOLUTION",
      "prompt": "During the French Revolution, who or what was…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The Bourbon king executed during the Revolution?",
          "answer": "Louis XVI"
        },
        {
          "question": "The machine used to behead enemies of the state?",
          "answer": "Guillotine"
        },
        {
          "question": "The general who commanded the National Guard and who served with Washington in the Revolutionary War?",
          "answer": "Marquis de Lafayette"
        },
        {
          "question": "The man who led the Committee of Public Safety during the Reign of Terror?",
          "answer": "Maximilien Robespierre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political group opposed by the Girondists, named for their high seating in the Jacobin Clubs?",
          "answer": "the Montagnards"
        },
        {
          "question": "The tripartite medieval assembly called in 1789 which launched the Revolution?",
          "answer": "Estates-General"
        },
        {
          "question": "The document, inspired by the Declaration of Independence, which stated the Revolution’s core values?",
          "answer": "Declaration of the Rights of Man and of the Citizen"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Swiss financier who was unable to solve France’s financial problems?",
          "answer": "Jacques Necker"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "GERMAN UNIFICATION",
      "prompt": "During the process of German unification, who or what was…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The first German chancellor who engineered unification?",
          "answer": "Otto von Bismarck"
        },
        {
          "question": "The militaristic north German state which led unification?",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Prussia"
        },
        {
          "question": "The nation led by Napoleon III that was defeated in 1871, leading to the proclamation of the Second Reich?",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "The territory formed from two border regions that was annexed by Germany from its western neighbor?",
          "answer": "Alsace-Lorraine"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Danish border region seized in a war by the two leading powers of the German Confederation?",
          "answer": "Schleswig-Holstein"
        },
        {
          "question": "The king who became the first German Emperor?",
          "answer": "Wilhelm I"
        },
        {
          "question": "The royal house of the new German Emperors?",
          "answer": "Hohenzollern"
        },
        {
          "question": "The 1866 battle that ended Austrian hegemony over the German states?",
          "answer": "Battle of Sadowa"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "HUNDRED YEARS WAR",
      "prompt": "During the Hundred Years War, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Peasant girl who helped France win the Battle of Orleans?",
          "answer": "Joan of Arc"
        },
        {
          "question": "English king whose claims to the throne of France began the war?",
          "answer": "Edward III"
        },
        {
          "question": "General who captured John II of France at the Battle of Poitiers?",
          "answer": "Edward the Black Prince"
        },
        {
          "question": "Missile weapon whose “long” variety is often miscredited as giving the English a decisive advantage over French knights?",
          "answer": "Bow"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty signed by the Queen of France that made Henry V heir to the throne?",
          "answer": "Treaty of Troyes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Spanish kingdom where the contemporary War of the Two Peters took place, later home to a princess who married Henry VIII?",
          "answer": "Aragon"
        },
        {
          "question": "French port city whose heroic surrendering “Burghers” were sculpted by Auguste Rodin?",
          "answer": "Calais"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the substance the “mad king” of France, Charles VI, believed he was made out of?",
          "answer": "glass"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "HITLER INVADES RUSSIA",
      "prompt": "During Hitler’s invasion of the Soviet Union, who or what…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the German code name for the invasion?",
          "answer": "Operation Barbarossa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the year the invasion was launched?",
          "answer": "1941"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the 1939 non-aggression pact that Hitler broke by invading the USSR?",
          "answer": "Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the city in southern Russia where an entire German army was forced to surrender in 1943?",
          "answer": "Stalingrad"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the former Russian capital that survived a 900-day siege by German forces?",
          "answer": "Leningrad"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the Soviet Field Marshal who commanded the counter-attack against Germany?",
          "answer": "Georgy Zhukov"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was a 1943 Soviet victory remembered as the largest tank battle in history?",
          "answer": "Battle of Kursk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Became the first German Field Marshal in history to surrender, after being surrounded by Soviet forces during Operation Uranus?",
          "answer": "Friedrich von Paulus SUPREME COURT IN THE 20 TH"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Winston Churchill",
      "prompt": "Concerning Winston Churchill’s career, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Political position he held during World War II and the 1950s as head of government of the United Kingdom.",
          "answer": "Prime Minister"
        },
        {
          "question": "Branch of the British armed forces that he praised for their performance against the Luftwaffe.",
          "answer": "Royal Air Force or RAF"
        },
        {
          "question": "1938 agreement, signed by Neville Chamberlain and Adolf Hitler, that he vocally opposed.",
          "answer": "Munich Agreement"
        },
        {
          "question": "Failed World War I campaign he organized as First Lord of the Admiralty, in which over 8,000 Australians died.",
          "answer": "Gallipoli campaign"
        },
        {
          "question": "Egyptian World War II battle, declared by Churchill to be “perhaps, the end of the beginning.”",
          "answer": "Second Battle of El Alamein"
        },
        {
          "question": "Labour Party leader who defeated him in 1945 and 1950 elections.",
          "answer": "Clement Attlee"
        },
        {
          "question": "War in which he was captured and held as a POW.",
          "answer": "Second Boer War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Deputy and Foreign Secretary who succeeded him in 1955, leading Britain during the Suez Crisis.",
          "answer": "Sir Anthony Eden"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "French Monarchs",
      "prompt": "In the Ancient Regime, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Despotic ruler known as the Sun King?",
          "answer": "Louis XIV"
        },
        {
          "question": "Queen executed in 1793 during the French Revolution?",
          "answer": "Marie Antoinette"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Bourbon king, who noted that “Paris is well worth a mass”?",
          "answer": [
            "Henry IV",
            "Henry of Navarre"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "House that often warred with France, whose Spanish branch included Charles V?",
          "answer": "Habsburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Canonized king who launched the Seventh Crusade?",
          "answer": [
            "Louis IX",
            "Saint Louis"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "House that ruled between the Capetian and Bourbon houses?",
          "answer": "House of Valois"
        },
        {
          "question": "King who won the battle of Marignano and joined the Ottomans in the Unholy Alliance?",
          "answer": "Francis I"
        },
        {
          "question": "King known for his plotting that fought against Charles the Bold of Burgundy?",
          "answer": [
            "Louis XI",
            "Louis the Spider"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Explorers of the New World",
      "prompt": "Which explorer of the New World...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Led the Corps of Discovery with Meriwether Lewis?",
          "answer": "William Clark"
        },
        {
          "question": "Abandoned the Santa Maria on Christmas Day, 1492, after it ran aground during his first voyage?",
          "answer": "Christopher Columbus or Cristobal Colon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was set adrift in 1611 by his mutinying crew in a Canadian bay now named for him?",
          "answer": "Henry Hudson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sought the Fountain of Youth on the first European expedition to Florida?",
          "answer": "Juan Ponce de Leon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Discovered and claimed Brazil for Portugal in 1500, then sailed around Africa to India?",
          "answer": "Pedro ‘Alvares Cabral"
        },
        {
          "question": "Landed in Newfoundland in 1497, sailing for Henry VII of England?",
          "answer": "John Cabot or Giovanni Caboto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first European to cross the Mississippi River, then was buried in the river?",
          "answer": "Hernando de Soto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first European to reach the Grand Canyon, while trying to find the Seven Cities of Gold?",
          "answer": "Francisco V’azques de Coronado"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Middle Ages English Rulers",
      "prompt": "Who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Died at Bosworth Field and was the third and last English king of his name?",
          "answer": "Richard III"
        },
        {
          "question": "Signed the Magna Carta in 1215?",
          "answer": "John Lackland or John Softsword"
        },
        {
          "question": "Clashed with Guthrum and was the only English king called “the Great”?",
          "answer": "Alfred the Great"
        },
        {
          "question": "Defeated the Scots at Falkirk and was nicknamed for his height?",
          "answer": [
            "Edward Longshanks",
            "Edward I"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Ordered the St. Brices Day Massacre and was nicknamed for his ill-counsel?",
          "answer": [
            "Aethelred the Unready",
            "Aethelred II"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Signed the Provisions of Oxford and clashed with Simon de Montfort?",
          "answer": "Henry III"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was born Nicholas Breakspear and became the only English Pope?",
          "answer": "Adrian IV"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ascended to the throne following the Anarchy and Treaty of Wallingford?",
          "answer": "Henry II"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Nicholas II",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Title held by Nicholas II as ruler of Russia.",
          "answer": "tsar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Conflict that Nicholas II lost, leading to his overthrow and the rise of the Soviet Union.",
          "answer": "World War I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Grandmother of Nicholas II, a long-lived Queen of Britain whose descendents married into many royal houses.",
          "answer": "Queen Victoria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian mystic who Nicholas employed to treat his son’s hemophilia.",
          "answer": "Grigori Rasputin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that defeated Nicholas’s Russia at the Battle of Tsushima Straits.",
          "answer": "Japan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynastic house that Nicholas II belonged to. It began to rule Russia in 1613.",
          "answer": "House of Romanov"
        },
        {
          "question": "Legislature that Nicholas was forced to convene after the Revolution of 1905.",
          "answer": "Duma"
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician that headed the Provisional Government after the abdication of Nicholas and was overthrown by the Bolsheviks, beginning the October Revolution.",
          "answer": "Alexander Kerensky"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "French Revolution",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "French King executed during the Revolution.",
          "answer": "Louis XVI"
        },
        {
          "question": "Parisian prison that was stormed at the beginning of the French Revolution.",
          "answer": "the Bastille Saint-Antoine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Popular, sharp method of execution, which became a symbol of the excessive violence during the Reign of Terror.",
          "answer": [
            "guillotine",
            "word forms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary who started the Reign of Terror, which ended with his execution.",
          "answer": "Maximilien Robespierre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Traditional subdivision of French society that was less powerful than the clergy and nobility.",
          "answer": "Third Estate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Radical journalist and revolutionary who was assassinated by Charlotte Corday in his bath.",
          "answer": "Jean-Paul Marat"
        },
        {
          "question": "Location of a 1789 oath to create a constitution, a pivotal event early in the Revolution.",
          "answer": [
            "a tennis court",
            "the Tennis Court Oath"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Coup against radical Jacobins that put an end to the Reign of Terror.",
          "answer": "Thermidorian Reaction"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Protestantism in France",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "”Reformed” group of Calvinists that fought with the French crown during the Wars of Religion and were protected by the Edict of Nantes [nahnt].",
          "answer": "Huguenots"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city that the Protestant Henry IV declared was “well worth a mass” on converting to Catholicism.",
          "answer": "Paris"
        },
        {
          "question": "”Sun King” who revoked the Edict of Nantes in 1685.",
          "answer": "Louis XIV"
        },
        {
          "question": "1572 massacre of French Protestants ordered by the Queen Mother, Catherine d’Medici.",
          "answer": "St. Bartholomew’s Day Massacre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty that supported the Protestants through its cadet House of Cond´e. It was the last royal house of France.",
          "answer": "House of Bourbon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cardinal who fought French Protestants while serving Louis XIII.",
          "answer": "Richelieu"
        },
        {
          "question": "1685 edict that revoked the Edict of Nantes.",
          "answer": "Edict of Fontainebleau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Port city that was a haven for French Protestants until its destruction by Louis XIII. It was reinforced by the English Duke of Buckingham.",
          "answer": "La Rochelle"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Genocide",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Genocide carried out by Nazi Germany against “undesirable” people.",
          "answer": "Holocaust or Shoah"
        },
        {
          "question": "Polish concentration camp, which included an extermination camp at Birkenau, used during that genocide.",
          "answer": "Auschwitz-Birkenau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dutch city where the International Criminal Court prosecutes perpetrators of genocide.",
          "answer": "The Hague"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ethnic group targeted by an Ottoman genocide during World War I, now denied by the Turkish government.",
          "answer": "Armenian people"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern country that was the site of the Holodomor famine and is the site of Russian military intervention.",
          "answer": "Ukraine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Western region of Sudan, subject to fighting between the government and Janjaweed militias.",
          "answer": "Darfur genocide"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sudanese President indicted by the ICC for that genocide.",
          "answer": "Omar al-Bashir"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern-day country where colonial Germans committed a genocide of the Herero and Namaqua people.",
          "answer": "Namibia"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "North Africa in World War II",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "British-controlled waterway connecting the Mediterranean and Red Seas, an essential target in North Africa.",
          "answer": "Suez Canal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that sent the Afrika Korps to fight in North Africa but was forced to retreat to allied Italy.",
          "answer": "Nazi Germany"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commander of the Afrika Korps who gained the nickname “Desert Fox” for his success in Africa.",
          "answer": "Erwin Rommel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Final British commander in North Africa. His Eighth Army won the Battle of El Alamein.",
          "answer": "Bernard Law Montgomery"
        },
        {
          "question": "British island with capital Valetta where submarines and airplanes targeted enemy shipping in the Mediterranean.",
          "answer": "Malta"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mediterranean island targeted by Operation Husky, which was launched from North Africa.",
          "answer": "Sicily"
        },
        {
          "question": "Operation name for the Anglo-American invasion of North Africa, which landed in French-held territory in November 1942.",
          "answer": [
            "Operation Torch",
            "Operation Gymnast"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Vital harbor lost by the British after the Battle of Gazala. Its defenders became known as the Desert Rats.",
          "answer": "Tobruk"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Soviet Union",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Successor state to the Soviet Union whose capital is Moscow.",
          "answer": "Russia or Russian Federation"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dictator who ordered the death of Leon Trotsky and was succeeded by Nikita Khrushchev.",
          "answer": "Joseph Vissarionovich Stalin"
        },
        {
          "question": "European country where the Soviets crushed Imre Nagy’s [nahj’s] rebellion in 1956.",
          "answer": "Hungary"
        },
        {
          "question": "1959 event in which Nixon and Khrushchev debated capitalism and communism in a model home.",
          "answer": "Kitchen Debate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Genocidal famine in Ukraine from 1932-33.",
          "answer": "Holodomor"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name for both US-Soviet treaties that limited ballistic missile production.",
          "answer": "SALT 1 and/or 2 or Strategic Arms Limitation Talks"
        },
        {
          "question": "1921 rebellion whose suppression led to the development of the New Economic Policy.",
          "answer": "Kronstadt Rebellion"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Labor and Revolt in the Nineteenth Century",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Philosopher of labor who worked with Engels on the Communist Manifesto.",
          "answer": "Karl Marx"
        },
        {
          "question": "Period of urban migration and swift technological improvement that began in Britain in the early 19th century.",
          "answer": "Industrial Revolution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Year in which Austria and Hungary gave up serfdom and revolutions occurred all over Europe during the “Spring of Nations.”",
          "answer": "1848"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where an 1871 socialist “Commune” was suppressed following its country’s loss to Prussia.",
          "answer": "Paris Commune"
        },
        {
          "question": "GermanKaiser,anemployerofOttovonBismarck,whoseattemptedassassinationsledtoacrackdown on socialists.",
          "answer": "Wilhelm I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Massacre of British protesters in 1819 that led to the Six Acts, restricting protests.",
          "answer": "Peterloo Massacre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hungarian revolutionary who briefly led the country and toured the United States after being exiled.",
          "answer": "Lajos Kossuth de Udvard et Kossuthfalva or Louis Kossuth"
        },
        {
          "question": "German customs union that bound its states together prior to the country’s unification.",
          "answer": "Zollverein"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Thirty Years’ War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Hapsburg country led during the war by Philip IV from Madrid.",
          "answer": "Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Official religion of possessions of the Hapsburg family, which opposed the Protestant Union.",
          "answer": "Roman Catholicism"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Red Eminence,” an adviser to Louis XIII who oversaw French intervention during the war.",
          "answer": "Cardinal Richelieu or Armand Jean du Plessis"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where regents were defenestrated, or tossed out of a third-story window, to begin the war.",
          "answer": "Prague"
        },
        {
          "question": "Peace negotiated to conclude the war, the result of the treaties of Osnabru¨ck and Mu¨nster.",
          "answer": "Peace of Westphalia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commander of Swedish forces during the Thirty Years’ War until his death at Lu¨tzen.",
          "answer": "Gustavus Adolphus"
        },
        {
          "question": "German city that was the site of a brutal 1631 sacking, the worst massacre of the war.",
          "answer": "Sack of Magdeburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "German town, the site of two key battles in the war: a 1634 victory in which tercios crushed the Swedish army, and a 1645 French victory.",
          "answer": "Battles of Nordlingen"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Russia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "“Terrible” tsar who killed his son and ruled Russia in the 16th century.",
          "answer": "Ivan the Terrible or Ivan IV"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion followed by the traveler Ibn Fadlan, which the Rus briefly considered converting to before they found out it prohibited alcohol.",
          "answer": "Islam"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tsar who opened Russia to the west with a Grand Embassy in the late 17th century.",
          "answer": "Peter the Great or Peter I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nobleman who built fake villages to impress Catherine the Great and names a battleship whose men mutinied in 1905.",
          "answer": [
            "Grigory Potemkin",
            "Battleship Potemkin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Viking chieftain who founded the Kievan Rus and names the dynasty before the Romanovs.",
          "answer": "Rurik"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mongol leader, the grandfather of Kublai Khan, who sent Subutai to attack the Kievan Rus in the 1220s.",
          "answer": [
            "Genghis Khan",
            "Chinggis Khan",
            "Temujin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mongol khan who, as the first leader of the Golden Horde, finished conquering Kievan Rus in 1237.",
          "answer": "Batu Khan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prince who defeated the Teutonic Knights at the Battle on the Ice at Lake Peipus.",
          "answer": "Alexander Nevsky"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "French Colonial History",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Founder of the Fifth Republic who gave Algeria its independence.",
          "answer": "Charles de Gaulle"
        },
        {
          "question": "Egyptian waterway targeted by France, Israel, and Great Britain in a 1956 Crisis.",
          "answer": [
            "Suez Canal",
            "Suez Crisis"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Colony whose independence movement was led by Ho Chi Minh.",
          "answer": "Vietnam or French Indochina"
        },
        {
          "question": "1954 battle in that colony in which France was defeated by Vo Nguyen Giap.",
          "answer": "Battle of Dien Bien Phu"
        },
        {
          "question": "Emperor who colonized Senegal and less successfully installed Maximilian I in Mexico.",
          "answer": "Napoleon III"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern African country that was formerly the French Upper Volta colony.",
          "answer": "Burkina Faso"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former French colony that faced a Tuareg rebellion aiming to establish the state of Azawad.",
          "answer": "Mali"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colonial border crisis in 1898 in which British and French troops stood off in Sudan.",
          "answer": "Fashoda incident or crisis, etc."
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Crimea",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "“Great” Russian empress who annexed the Crimea in 1783.",
          "answer": "Catherine the Great"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crimean city where Roosevelt, Churchill, and Stalin met in a 1945 conference.",
          "answer": "Yalta"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ottoman sultan who annexed the Crimean Khanate in 1475.",
          "answer": "Mehmed the Conqueror or Mehmed II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crimean War nurse who became known as “the Lady with the Lamp” and modernized war nursing practices",
          "answer": "Florence Nightingale"
        },
        {
          "question": "HIghest British honor, created during the Crimean War, whose medals are legendary made from stolen Crimean cannon.",
          "answer": "Victoria Cross"
        },
        {
          "question": "Port city that was the subject of a year-long Franco-British siege during the Crimean War.",
          "answer": "Siege of Sevastopol"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crimean War battle during that siege that inspired Tennyson’s “Charge of the Light Brigade.”",
          "answer": "Battle of Balaclava"
        },
        {
          "question": "Field Marshal whose Highlanders formed the Thin Red Line in that battle.",
          "answer": "Colin Campbell"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "European Fields",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Decisive August 1485 battle of the Wars of the Roses.",
          "answer": "Battle of Bosworth Field"
        },
        {
          "question": "English king who met Francis I at the Field of the Cloth of Gold and married six times.",
          "answer": "Henry VIII"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the Huns who was defeated at the Catalaunian Fields in the Battle of Chalons [sha-lone].",
          "answer": "Attila the Hun"
        },
        {
          "question": "Farming practice of planting fields of wheat, then beans, then nothing, to help replenish the soil.",
          "answer": "crop rotation"
        },
        {
          "question": "War in which the poem “In Flanders Fields” was written after the Battle of Ypres [eep].",
          "answer": "World War I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Paradise of Greek myth where heroes not sent to Hades were sent.",
          "answer": [
            "Elysian Fields",
            "Elysium"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Former Serbian territory where a 1389 battle of the Field of Blackbirds took place.",
          "answer": [
            "Kosovo",
            "Battle of Kosovo Polje"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "English city where an 1819 massacre took place in St. Peter’s Field.",
          "answer": "Manchester"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Italian Wars",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City aided by Genoa and Venice in its war against Florence; it is home to a famously leaning tower.",
          "answer": "Pisa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Artist who escaped to France with his Mona Lisa after the Battle of Marignano.",
          "answer": [
            "Leonardo da Vinci",
            "either",
            "both names"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Title held by the ruler of Venice.",
          "answer": "Doge"
        },
        {
          "question": "City-state led by Ludovico Sforza at the start of the Wars.",
          "answer": "Milan"
        },
        {
          "question": "League initially formed by the Papal States to oppose Venice; it names a 1508-1516 war.",
          "answer": "War of the League of Cambrai"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Warrior Pope” who organized that League and ordered the painting of the Sistine Chapel.",
          "answer": "Julius II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Decisive 1525 battle that assured Habsburg power in Italy after the Treaty of Madrid.",
          "answer": "Battle of Pavia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Genoese admiral who kicked the French out of Genoa and allied with Charles V.",
          "answer": "Andrea Doria"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Communism in Europe",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Final leader of the Soviet Union; he was succeeded by Boris Yeltsin.",
          "answer": "Mikhail Gorbachev"
        },
        {
          "question": "Faction of communists during the Russian Revolution who prevailed over the Mensheviks.",
          "answer": [
            "Bolsheviks",
            "Bolshevists"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Period of political liberalization in Czechoslovakia that began after the election of Alexander Dubˇcek [doob-check] in 1968.",
          "answer": "Prague Spring"
        },
        {
          "question": "Collective defense treaty signed by eight communist countries after World War II, created in response to NATO.",
          "answer": "Warsaw Pact"
        },
        {
          "question": "East German secret police service whose name is an abbreviation of the German for “State Security Service.”",
          "answer": "Stasi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician and labour activist who founded the Soviet Bloc’s first independent trade union, known as Solidarity.",
          "answer": "Lech Walesa , but be lenient"
        },
        {
          "question": "Anti-Communist dictator and “Conducator” of Romania during World War II",
          "answer": "Ion Antonescu"
        },
        {
          "question": "First communist leader of Bulgaria; he was initially arrested for the Reichstag fire in 1933.",
          "answer": "Georgi Dimitrov"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Modern German Politics",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Center-right party, the traditional rival of the Social Democratic Party, that currently holds power.",
          "answer": [
            "Christian Democratic Party of Germany",
            "Christian Democrats",
            "CDU",
            "Christlich Demokratische Union Deutschlands"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Current Chancellor of Germany, the first woman to hold the position.",
          "answer": "Angela Merkel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Elected Parliament of Germany, which meets in the Reichstag in Berlin.",
          "answer": "Bundestag"
        },
        {
          "question": "Environmentalist party that merged with Alliance 90 in 1993.",
          "answer": [
            "Alliance 90/The Greens",
            "Green Party",
            "Bu¨ndnis 90/Die Gru¨nen"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Racist, far-right party founded in 2013 that won its first 94 seats in Parliament in 2017.",
          "answer": [
            "Alternative for Germany or AfD",
            "Alternative fu¨r Deutschland"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Chancellor of West Germany whose Finance Minister Ludwig Erhard engineered an “economic miracle” after the war.",
          "answer": "Konrad Adenauer"
        },
        {
          "question": "Chancellor who led reunified Germany after the fall of the Berlin Wall.",
          "answer": "Helmut Kohl"
        },
        {
          "question": "Current President of German Parliament and former Finance Minister who resigned as party leader in 2000 amidst scandal.",
          "answer": "Wolfgang Schauble , but be lenient"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "1940 Fall of France",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Axis power that occupied a small section of southeast France after Germany conquered France.",
          "answer": "Italy"
        },
        {
          "question": "French general who evacuated to London during the Fall and later led Free France.",
          "answer": "Charles de Gaulle"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where over 300,000 people were evacuated across the English Channel at the end of May 1940.",
          "answer": "Dunkirk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Forest on the Belgian-French border that the German blitzkrieg stormed through.",
          "answer": "Ardennes Forest"
        },
        {
          "question": "Line of French forts and bunkers that the Germans avoided by invading through that forest.",
          "answer": "Maginot Line"
        },
        {
          "question": "armistice.",
          "answer": "Compiegne"
        },
        {
          "question": "Algerian city where the British attacked the French navy in July 1940 to prevent the Nazis from gaining the ships.",
          "answer": "Mers-el-Kebir"
        },
        {
          "question": "French port city where the Free French scuttled its own fleet in 1942 foiling Operation Anton.",
          "answer": "Toulon"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Roanoke Colony",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern-day state where the Lost Colony of Roanoke was located in the Outer Banks.",
          "answer": "North Carolina"
        },
        {
          "question": "Explorer who owned the charter over Roanoke; unrelatedly, he was twice imprisoned in the Tower of London.",
          "answer": "Sir Walter Raleigh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Foreign fleet whose 1588 attack on England delayed a resupply fleet to Roanoke.",
          "answer": "Spanish Armada"
        },
        {
          "question": "First English colonist born in the New World, who was born at Roanoke.",
          "answer": "Virginia Dare"
        },
        {
          "question": "Privateer who took the original colonists back to England in 1586, less than a decade after circumnavigating the globe.",
          "answer": "Sir Francis Drake"
        },
        {
          "question": "Word carved into a fencepost, providing the only hint for where the Lost Colonists went.",
          "answer": "CROATOAN"
        },
        {
          "question": "Symbol consisting of four V-shaped arrows that was to be carved if the colonists encountered trouble; no such symbol was found.",
          "answer": "Maltese cross"
        },
        {
          "question": "Surname of Richard, who led the first fleet of colonists to Roanoke, and William, a British PM who led the “Ministry of All the Talents.”",
          "answer": [
            "Grenville",
            "Sir Richard Grenville",
            "William Grenville, Lord Grenville"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Eighty Years’ War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire that held the Netherlands as a personal union prior to the Eighty Years’ War.",
          "answer": "Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynastic house from Austria that, at the time, ruled that country.",
          "answer": [
            "Habsburgs",
            "Hapsburgs"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Largely German empire of which the Netherlands was officially a part until 1648.",
          "answer": [
            "Holy Roman Empire",
            "Sacrum Imperium Romanum",
            "Heiliges R¨omisches Reich"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the Dutch Revolt, the father of the Netherlands, who was assassinated by Balthasar G´erard.",
          "answer": [
            "William I",
            "William of Orange",
            "William the Silent",
            "William the Taciturn",
            "Willem de Zwijger",
            "Willem van Oranje"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Kingdom that lost control of the Malabar Coast and the Cape of Good Hope as part of a war with the Dutch.",
          "answer": "Portugal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fireships that worked as floating bombs during the Siege of Antwerp; ships of the same name fought the Spanish Armada.",
          "answer": [
            "hellburners",
            "hellebranders"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty, part of the larger Peace of Westphalia, that established the Dutch Republic in 1648.",
          "answer": "Peace of Mu¨nster"
        },
        {
          "question": "Confederation of Dutch nobles led by Willem Bloys van Treslong that seized Brielle after losing access to British ports.",
          "answer": [
            "Sea Beggars",
            "Watergeuzen",
            "Gueux de mer"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Crimean War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Sea into which the Crimean Peninsula juts, forming the naval theater of the war.",
          "answer": "Black Sea"
        },
        {
          "question": "British nurse who earned the nickname Lady with the Lamp during the war.",
          "answer": "Florence Nightingale"
        },
        {
          "question": "Major European power that allied with Britain, Sardinia, and the Ottomans in the war.",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian city besieged by Lord Raglan; battles in that siege included Balaclava.",
          "answer": "Siege of Sevastopol"
        },
        {
          "question": "Force whose ill-fated charge at the Battle of Balaclava was immortalized in a Tennyson poem",
          "answer": "Charge of the Light Brigade"
        },
        {
          "question": "Officer who led that charge on orders from Lord Lucan, passed incorrectly through Captain Nolan.",
          "answer": [
            "James Thomas Brudenell, 7th Earl Cardigan",
            "either",
            "both names",
            "Lord Cardigan"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "November 1853 naval battle against the Ottomans that incited Britain to join the war.",
          "answer": "Battle of Sinope"
        },
        {
          "question": "Photographer whose Valley of the Shadow of Death was taken at Balaclava.",
          "answer": "Roger Fenton"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Start of World War II",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Strategy of “lightning war” used by Nazi Germany in its opening invasions.",
          "answer": "blitzkrieg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that was invaded by the Nazis to start the war after the Gleiwitz incident.",
          "answer": "Poland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Date on which that invasion began.",
          "answer": "September 1, 1939"
        },
        {
          "question": "Neutrality pact between the Soviets and Nazis that was secretly signed a week before that invasion.",
          "answer": "Molotov-von Ribbentrop Pact"
        },
        {
          "question": "Defensive line built by the French in the 1930s to buy time for mobilization; it was weak along the Ardennes, which the Nazis exploited.",
          "answer": "Maginot Line"
        },
        {
          "question": "War between the Soviets and Finland in the opening months of World War II, followed by the Continuation War.",
          "answer": "Winter War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for the first eight months of the war which were, except for a brief French invasion into southwestern Germany, mostly quiet on the western front.",
          "answer": [
            "Phony War",
            "Sitzkrieg"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "That brief French offensive, which was aborted after the Nazis quickly closed the eastern front.",
          "answer": "Saar Offensive"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "FDR’s Cabinet",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Cabinet position briefly held by Nuremberg Trial prosecutor Robert Jackson, the head of the Justice Department.",
          "answer": "Attorney General"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cabinet position created in 1947 and first held by James Forrestal, who had been FDR’s Secretary of the Navy.",
          "answer": "Secretary of Defense"
        },
        {
          "question": "First woman to serve in the Cabinet; she served for FDR’s entire administration.",
          "answer": "Frances Perkins"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cabinet position held by that woman.",
          "answer": "Secretary of Labor"
        },
        {
          "question": "Agriculture and Commerce Secretary who also served as VP for FDR’s third term.",
          "answer": "Henry Agard Wallace"
        },
        {
          "question": "Secretary of State who won a Nobel Peace Prize in 1945.",
          "answer": "Cordell Hull"
        },
        {
          "question": "Co-namesake of a university in Daytona Beach who coined the term “Black Cabinet” for FDR’s African-American advisers.",
          "answer": "Mary McLeod Bethune"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treasury Secretary and New Deal architect who proposed demilitarizing Nazi Germany.",
          "answer": "Henry Morgenthau, Jr."
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Fascist Italy",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city that was the target of a fascist march.",
          "answer": "Rome"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fascist leader of Italy during World War II, called “Il Duce” [eel doo-chay].",
          "answer": "Benito Mussolini"
        },
        {
          "question": "Volunteer militia, named for the color of their uniform, that supported that leader.",
          "answer": [
            "Blackshirts",
            "Milizia Volontaria per la Sicurezza Nazionale",
            "MVSN",
            "Voluntary Militia for National Security",
            "Camicie Nere",
            "Camicia Nera",
            "squadristi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Expansionist goal promoted by Italy’s Spazio vitale [spatz-ee-oh vee-TAL-ay] and Nazi Germany’s Lebensraum [lay-bens-raum].",
          "answer": "living space"
        },
        {
          "question": "1939 alliance between Italy and Germany negotiated by Galeazzo Ciano.",
          "answer": [
            "Pact of Steel",
            "stahlpakt",
            "Patto d’Acciaio"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1929 treaty that settled the Roman Question.",
          "answer": [
            "Lateran Treaty",
            "Patti Lateranensi",
            "Pacta Lateranensia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "German puppet state that controlled the Northern half of Italy, established after an Allied invasion.",
          "answer": [
            "Republic of Salo",
            "Italian Social Republic"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "“Father” of Italian fascism who ghostwrote a portion of The Doctrine of Fascism for an Italian Prime Minister.",
          "answer": "Giovanni Gentile"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "European Inventors and Engineers",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Physician who suggested a “simple mechanism” for decapitation in the French Revolution; the device shares his name.",
          "answer": [
            "Joseph-Ignace Guillotin",
            "guillotine"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "German who developed the moveable type printing press.",
          "answer": "Johannes Gutenberg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Swedish businessman who owned Bofors and patented dynamite.",
          "answer": "Alfred Nobel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Scottish chemist who improved on the Newcomen steam engine and names the SI unit of power.",
          "answer": "James Watt"
        },
        {
          "question": "German who invented a namesake no-spark combustion engine and died at sea mysteriously in 1913.",
          "answer": "Rudolf Diesel"
        },
        {
          "question": "English “traitor” who memorized the designs of the Arkwright spinning frame to build textile mills in New England.",
          "answer": "Samuel Slater"
        },
        {
          "question": "English engineer of the Great Western Railway who tunneled under the Thames in the 1830s.",
          "answer": "Isambard Kingdom Brunel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian aviation family of Andrei, who reverse-engineered the B-29, and Alexei, who designed the first supersonic passenger jet.",
          "answer": "Tupolev family"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Explorers of the New World",
      "prompt": "Name the explorer who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Brought a few dozen slaves back with him on the Nin˜a and Pinta after his 1492 voyage to the New World.",
          "answer": "Christopher Columbus or Cristobal Colon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Established the Vinland colony as the first European in North America around 1000 AD.",
          "answer": "Leif Erikson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Briefly governed Puerto Rico and sought the Fountain of Youth in Florida.",
          "answer": "Juan Ponce de Leon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mapped the Gulf of Saint Lawrence and claimed Canada for France.",
          "answer": "Jacques Cartier"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crossed Panama in 1513 to become the first European to reach the Pacific through the New World.",
          "answer": "Vasco Nu´n˜ez de Balboa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Accidentally reached Brazil, claiming it for Portugal, on his way to India in 1500.",
          "answer": "Pedro Alvares Cabral"
        },
        {
          "question": "Helped Pizarro conquer the Incas and was the first European to cross the Mississippi River.",
          "answer": "Hernando de Soto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Executed a native guide he called “the Turk” after they discovered that Quivira, in modern Kansas, was not a city of gold.",
          "answer": "Francisco V´azquez de Coronado"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Contemporaries of Stalin",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Man who preceded Stalin as leader of the Soviet Union.",
          "answer": "Vladimir Lenin or Vladimir Ilyich Ulyanov"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rival who was executed by Ramon Mercader in Mexico in 1940.",
          "answer": [
            "Leon Trotsky",
            "Lev Davidovich Bronstein"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Yugoslavian president who told Stalin “Stop sending people to kill me” after their ideological split.",
          "answer": [
            "Josip Broz Tito",
            "either",
            "both names"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "German Field Marshall, captured at Stalingrad, who Stalin refused to trade for his own captured son.",
          "answer": "Friedrich Paulus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary who supposedly wrote a 1924 letter to British communists and was executed in a show trial in 1936.",
          "answer": [
            "Grigory Zinoviev",
            "Hirsch Apfelbaum"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician whose 1934 murder at the Smolny Institute was probably ordered by Stalin and definitely led to the Great Purge.",
          "answer": [
            "Sergei Kirov",
            "Sergei Kostrikov"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Head of the NKVD who became First Deputy Premier after Stalin’s death but was ousted and executed in 1953.",
          "answer": "Lavrentiy Beria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Editor of Pravda and theorist of “socialism in one country” who was executed after the last Moscow Show Trial.",
          "answer": "Nikolay Bukharin"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ronald Reagan’s Foreign Policy",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Russian premier told to “tear down” the Berlin Wall.",
          "answer": "Mikhail Gorbachev"
        },
        {
          "question": "Space-based missile defense system sought by Reagan.",
          "answer": [
            "Strategic Defense Initiative",
            "SDI",
            "Star Wars"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "South African cleric and Nobel laureate who condemned Reagan as “utterly racist” for refusing to fight apartheid.",
          "answer": "Archbishop Desmond Tutu"
        },
        {
          "question": "April 1986 terrorist attack in Germany that killed 2 US soldiers and led Reagan to bomb Libya.",
          "answer": "West Berlin discotheque bombing"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the New Jewel Movement whose death led to the invasion of Grenada.",
          "answer": "Maurice Bishop"
        },
        {
          "question": "National Security Advisor who resigned after organizing the Iran-Contra affair with Oliver North; his conviction on obstruction charges was reversed.",
          "answer": "John Poindexter"
        },
        {
          "question": "German town where Reagan visited a cemetery and claimed that young SS troops were “victims of Nazism” in 1985.",
          "answer": "Bitburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Central American dictator who Reagan claimed was “getting a bum rap” about his genocide of the Ixil and Maya people.",
          "answer": "Efrain Rios Montt"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Regarding Belgium, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the regarding belgium, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Status of not picking a side which Belgium was required to maintain under the Treaty of London",
          "answer": [
            "Neutral",
            "neutrality"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city that serves as the administrative center of the European Union",
          "answer": "Brussels"
        },
        {
          "question": "Small neighbor nation of which the French-speaking part was ceded to Belgium after the 1839 revolution",
          "answer": "Grand Duchy of Luxembourg"
        },
        {
          "question": "1885 conference formalizing the Scramble for Africa in which Belgium participated",
          "answer": [
            "Berlin Conference",
            "West Africa Conference",
            "Congo Conference"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "King who, once in control of the Congo Free State, ordered his Force Publique to cut off workers' hands",
          "answer": "Leopold II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Post-World War Two multinational organization formed by the 1951 Treaty of Paris of which Belgium was a founding member",
          "answer": [
            "European Coal and Steel Community",
            "ECSC"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Nationalistic opera by Daniel Auber which helped spark its 1830 revolution",
          "answer": [
            "The Mute Girl of Portici",
            "The Dumb Girl of Portici",
            "La muette de Portici",
            "Masaniello"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Political crisis that forced a king of Belgium to abdicate for allegedly working with Nazi Germany",
          "answer": [
            "The Royal Question",
            "Question royale",
            "Koningskwestie 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 1 Indira Gandhi"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Fascist Italy",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Dictator, known as \"Il Duce,\" who seize control of Italy in 1925",
          "answer": "Benito Mussolini"
        },
        {
          "question": "Paramilitary wing of the Fascist Party which helped that leader seize power during the March on Rome",
          "answer": [
            "Blackshirts",
            "Camicie Nere",
            "CCNN",
            "squadristi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Italian king who ordered the arrest of his prime minister in 1943",
          "answer": "Victor Emmanuel III or Vittorio Emanuele III"
        },
        {
          "question": "1939 agreement that created an official alliance between Italy and Germany",
          "answer": [
            "Pact of Steel",
            "Pact of Friendship and Alliance between Germany and Italy"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Pope who issued Non abbiamo bisogno to denounce Fascist persecution of the church",
          "answer": "Pope Pius XI"
        },
        {
          "question": "Raid led by Otto Skorzeny to rescue an Italian leader imprisoned at a remote mountain plateau",
          "answer": "Gran Sasso Raid"
        },
        {
          "question": "German puppet state established after the Armistice of Cassibile",
          "answer": [
            "Republic of Salo",
            "Italian Socialist Republic",
            "RSI"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "September 1943 uprising against German forces occupying the capital of Campania",
          "answer": [
            "Four Days of Naples",
            "Quattro giornate di Napoli 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 5"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Regarding Margaret Thatcher, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the regarding margaret thatcher, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Sovereign country she led from London",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland",
            "Britain",
            "Great Britain"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Irish independence organization that attempted to kill her at Brighton",
          "answer": [
            "Provisional Irish Republican Army",
            "IRA"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Archipelago she invaded after it was seized by Argentina",
          "answer": [
            "Falkland Islands",
            "Falklands",
            "Islas Malvinas"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Shakespeare-inspired term for a period of strikes that led to her becoming PM",
          "answer": "Winter of Discontent"
        },
        {
          "question": "President of the United Mine Workers who led an 1984-85 strike against her government",
          "answer": "Arthur Scargill"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former PM she defeated in 1975 to become leader of the Conservative party",
          "answer": "Edward Heath"
        },
        {
          "question": "Controversial tax imposed on Scotland that was replaced by the Council Tax",
          "answer": [
            "Community Charge",
            "poll tax"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Secretary of State for the Environment who seized control of the Conservative party from Thatcher in 1990",
          "answer": "Michael Heseltine 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 7"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Mafia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Largest city in Nevada where several families set up casinos following the legalization of gambling",
          "answer": "Las Vegas"
        },
        {
          "question": "European nation from which many of the early mafia immigrated from the city of Palermo",
          "answer": "Italy or Italian Republic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Traditional position in the mob that often serves as the boss's right hand and is named for the Italian word for \"advisor\"",
          "answer": "Consigliere"
        },
        {
          "question": "Two-word Italian language term that translates to \"our thing\" used by mob members to refer to organization",
          "answer": "Cosa Nostra"
        },
        {
          "question": "1970 act drafted by G. Robert Blakey that allowed courts to try mob bosses for ordering their underlings to commit crimes",
          "answer": [
            "RICO Act",
            "Racketeer Influenced and Corrupt Organizations Act"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Boss of the Gambino family who organized the murder of Paul Castellano and was sentenced to life in prison in 1992",
          "answer": "John Gotti"
        },
        {
          "question": "Governing body founded by Lucky Luciano including representatives from each of the Five Families",
          "answer": "The Commission"
        },
        {
          "question": "1957 meeting held in New York state that resulted in the arrest of over 60 bosses",
          "answer": "Apalachin meeting 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 9"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Iron Curtain",
      "prompt": "Concerning the ideological division of Europe during the Cold War, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Polish capital which names a \"Pact\" of Communist nations led by the Soviet Union.",
          "answer": [
            "Warsaw",
            "Warsaw Pact"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "British prime minister who coined the term \"Iron Curtain\" in a 1946 speech.",
          "answer": "Winston Churchill or Winston Leonard Spencer Churchill"
        },
        {
          "question": "1949 Collective Security organization including most Western European nations and the United States.",
          "answer": [
            "North Atlantic Treaty Organization",
            "NATO"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Conference in Crimea where the Allies agreed on how to split Europe.",
          "answer": [
            "Yalta Conference",
            "Argonaut"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Movement\" advocated by the likes of Kwame Nkrumah and Josip Tito as an alternative to the Eastern and Western blocs.",
          "answer": [
            "Non-Aligned Movement",
            "NAM"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Nation whose dictator Enver Hoxha [[HOH-shah]] re-aligned his state from the USSR to Communist China in the 1960s.",
          "answer": "People's Socialist Republic of Albania or Republika Popullore Socialiste e Shqipërisë"
        },
        {
          "question": "East German prime minister whose forced resignation in 1989 paved the way for a unified Germany.",
          "answer": "Erich Honecker or Erich Ernst Paul Honecker"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Doctrine\" named for an American singer which Mikhail Gorbachev adopted, allowing neighbors to deal with their own internal affairs.",
          "answer": "Sinatra Doctrine"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Iroquois Confederacy",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Native American Confederacy, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "U.S. state which contained the heartland of the Iroquois Confederacy's territory.",
          "answer": "New York"
        },
        {
          "question": "European colonizer and traditional ally of the Iroquois who fought alongside the Confederacy in the French and Indian War.",
          "answer": [
            "England",
            "Great Britain",
            "the United Kingdom"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Narrow, single room building which served as the primary quarters for the Iroquois.",
          "answer": "Longhouses"
        },
        {
          "question": "Animal whose pelt was traded by the League, later fighting a namesake war with the Hurons and the French for control of it.",
          "answer": [
            "Beaver",
            "Beaver War"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Eastern member of the Iroquois Confederacy which were led by Joseph Brant.",
          "answer": [
            "Mohawk",
            "Kanienʼkeháka"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "18th century British act forbidding white settlement west of the Appalachians, intending to protect the \"Indian Reserve.\"",
          "answer": "Royal Proclamation of 1763"
        },
        {
          "question": "Collective term describing the crops maize, beans, and squash, which Iroquoian society relied on.",
          "answer": "Three Sisters"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ritualistic wars fought by the Iroquois to replace members killed in battle or by disease.",
          "answer": "Mourning Wars"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Samurai",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Samurai, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Medieval class of European warrior with whom the samurai are often compared.",
          "answer": [
            "Knight",
            "Knighthood"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Emperor who quashed the samurai-led Satsuma Rebellion following his namesake \"Restoration.\"",
          "answer": "Emperor Meiji"
        },
        {
          "question": "Curved, single-edged sword wielded by samurai and longer than a tachi but shorter than an odachi.",
          "answer": "Katana or uchigatana"
        },
        {
          "question": "General term for the moral code followed by samurai, often equated to western chivalry.",
          "answer": "Bushido"
        },
        {
          "question": "Feudal landholders who paid a fee to retain samurai in their armed forces.",
          "answer": "Daimyo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Masterless samurai who often worked as mercenaries or bandits in feudal Japan.",
          "answer": "Ronin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Composite bow traditionally wielded by samurai most often used to face other, well armored samurai.",
          "answer": "Yumi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Specific sites where, according to tradition, samurai would try out the effectiveness of a new katana by killing random passerby.",
          "answer": [
            "Crossroads",
            "Kōsaten",
            "or Tsujigiri"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man successfully negotiated his opponents’ evacuation of Chippenham in the\nTreaty of Wedmore [WEDD-more]. This man, who translated the first English versions of\nPastoral Care and The (20 pts) ",
        "Consolation of Philosophy, was the subject of a biography by\nAsser [ASS-urr]. This victor at Edington established the limits of the (10 pts) ",
        "Danelaw [DANElaw] by defeating Guthrum [GOOTH-rumm]. For 10 points, name this King of Wessex whose\nerudition and successful defense against Vikings made him the first person known as “King of\nEngland” and only one called “the Great.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Alfred the Great",
        "Alfred",
        "Alfred I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This product was blended with more palatable herbs in order to create madak [mahdokk]. The two principal areas of modern creation of this product are called the Golden\nCrescent and the Golden Triangle. This product names a conflict during which the (20 pts) ",
        "Taku forts were destroyed that was sparked by the boarding of the H. M. S. Arrow. A letter\nto Queen Victoria asking why this commodity was legal in her country was written by (10 pts) ",
        "Lin Zexu, who angered British merchants by destroying large amounts of it. For 10 points,\nidentify this narcotic drug whose trade sparked two wars between China and Britain."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "opium",
        "heroin",
        "yapian",
        "Opium Wars"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A king of this nation became known as “the desired” by his supporters after he and his\nfather were forced to abdicate at Bayonne and were replaced by Joseph (20 pts) ",
        "Bonaparte. The\nensuing invasion of this country was referred to as an “Ulcer” by Napoleon. The Duke of\nWellington defeated French forces in this nation with help from irregulars who launched a\n“little war” that is the origin of the word (10 pts) ",
        "“guerrilla.” For 10 points, much of the fighting\nduring the Peninsular War occurred in what country that borders Portugal?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Kingdom of Spain",
        "Spain",
        "Reino de Espana",
        "Espana"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was the Prime Minister when the common law rules for insanity defenses were developed, following Daniel M’Naghten’s murder of this man’s private secretary Edward Drummond. This man precipitated the (20 pts)",
        "Bedchamber Crisis when he demanded the removal of Whigs from Queen Victoria’s personal retinue. His Tamworth Manifesto organized the (10 pts)",
        "Conservative Party, and he attempted to use the Irish potato famine as a reason to repeal the Corn Laws. For 10 points, name this British Prime Minister who lends his first name to the London police force."
      ],
      "answer": "Robert Peel"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Duchy of Savoy was assured independence after this King’s forces won at the Battle of St. Quentin. His signing of the Treaty of Joinville prompted another ruler to sign the Treaty of Nonsuch. A revolt against the forces of this ruler sparked the (20 pts)",
        "Eighty Years’ War. This man’s brother John of Austria won the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Lepanto during his reign. The Battle of Gravelines prevented this man’s fleet from rendezvousing with the Duke of Parma and invading England. For 10 points, name this son of Charles V, the king of Spain who sent the Spanish Armada."
      ],
      "answer": "Philip II of Spain"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The head of the losing commander at this battle was sent to Maroboduus, the king of the Marcomanni. Segestes, the begrudging father-in-law of this battle’s victor, tried to warn the losing commander prior to this battle, which mostly took place at (20 pts)",
        "Kalkriese Hill. At the subsequent Battle of the Weser River, Germanicus recovered a standard lost at this battle. After this battle, Augustus reportedly shouted (10 pts)",
        "“Varus, give me back my legions!” For 10 points, identify this 9 AD battle in which Arminius’ Germanic forces successfully ambushed three Roman legions."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Teutoburg Forest"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The bull Cum Nimis Absurdum created one of these places that was subject to the flooding of the Tiber. A famous family took its name from the “red shield” hanging above their house in one of these places. The common name for these places derives from the area around a foundry in (20 pts)",
        "Venice. During World War II, Jurgen Stroop burnt one of these places to crush an (10 pts)",
        "uprising of prisoners bound for Treblinka. Residents of these places were often obliged to wear yellow clothing. For 10 points, name these districts to which Jews were confined in medieval Europe."
      ],
      "answer": "Jewish ghettos"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A ruler of this house was troubled by the Tour de Nesle affair and lost the Battle of Golden Spurs. That ruler ordered Jacques de Molay burned at the stake and oversaw the papacy’s move to (20 pts)",
        "Avignon. The Albigensian Crusade occurred during this house's rule. This dynasty’s founder succeeded Louis V, the last (10 pts)",
        "Carolingian king. It included Philip IV and the canonized Louis IX, and it preceded the House of Valois. For 10 points, name this French ruling house founded by a man named Hugh."
      ],
      "answer": "House of Capet"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Navigation Acts supported this policy, for which Jean-Baptiste Colbert advocated as Louis XIV’s Finance Minister. This practice’s emphasis on (20 pts)",
        "trade balance contrasts with the Physiocratic view that labor created national wealth. Colonial expansion and high (10 pts)",
        "tariffs were trademarks of, for ten points, what economic practice in which countries manipulated their economies to gain more monetary wealth than rival nations, which dominated Europe in the 17th and 18th centuries?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "mercantilism",
        "bullionism"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man forced Henri, duc de Rohan, to agree to the Peace of Alais. Pere Joseph was a prominent ally of this man, nicknamed for the grey robe that he wore as a Capuchin friar. (20 pts)",
        "Marie de Medici’s exile was due to her involvement in a conspiracy to remove this leader, the Day of the Dupes. The siege of the Huguenot castle of La (10 pts)",
        "Rochelle was led by this man, who was also known as the “Red Eminence”. He was succeeded by Mazarin in his highest post. For ten points, name this powerful chief minister of Louis XIII, a French cardinal."
      ],
      "answer": "Cardinal Richelieu"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One participant in this event secured a commitment to have its lease at Port Arthur restored. This event featured a broken commitment from one party to reorganize the Lublin Committee “on a broader democratic basis,” and set the (20 pts)",
        "Curzon Line as the eastern border of Poland. This event, codenamed Argonaut, featured one participant’s pledge to attack (10 pts)",
        "Japan after the surrender of Nazi Germany, and it was followed up five months later by a meeting at Potsdam. For ten points, name this February 1945 meeting between Stalin, Churchill, and Roosevelt which took place on the Crimean Peninsula."
      ],
      "answer": "Yalta Conference"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Lamfalussy process was used to develop the financial regulations used by this group. The third Delors Commission ratified the existence of this entity. The Copenhagen (20 pts)",
        "criteria are used to determine eligibility to join this group, and the Schengen Agreement allows for freedom of travel between members of this group. This organization was preceded by the (10 pts)",
        "ECSC and the EEC and was formally created by the 1993 Treaty of Maastricht. For ten points, name this organization of countries which includes France, Britain, and Germany."
      ],
      "answer": "European Union or EU"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This work describes public credit as “a very important source of strength and security,” noting that “timely disbursements to prepare for danger frequently prevent much greater disbursements to repel it.” It describes a potential “formal and (20 pts)",
        "permanent despotism” “on the ruins of Public Liberty,” and it re-states the importance of neutrality in the ongoing war between (10 pts)",
        "France and Britain, despite an alliance with France. Foreign alliances and political parties are warned against in, for ten points, what address that opens with a decline to run for a third term as President in 1796?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "George Washington’s farewell address",
        "descriptions"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of these people had an affair with Hippolyte Charles that was widely publicized in Europe. The Souvenir de la Malmaison rose is named after the house that that person stayed in after she lost this title. The 1814 Treaty of (20 pts)",
        "Fontainebleau allowed one holder of this title to inherit power after the War of the Sixth Coalition. The phrase “I married a womb” was used to describe the second of these people, (10 pts)",
        "Marie Louise. For ten points, name these two women, including Josephine de Beauharnais, who were well-connected with a certain French emperor."
      ],
      "answer": "wives of Napoleon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Donald Cunnell wounded this man a week before being killed at Wervik. This man’s cousin Wolfram was placed in charge of Operation Rugen, carried out by the Condor Legion. He served with his brother Lothar in (20 pts)",
        "Jasta [yah-sta] 11. Lanoe Hawker, the so-called “British Boelcke,” was killed by this instigator of “Bloody April,” whose pursuit of a Sopwith Camel ended with his defeat near (10 pts)",
        "Amiens [ah-mee-ehn] in April 1918 by Roy Brown. For ten points, name this leader of the Flying Circus, a distinguished German ace of World War I."
      ],
      "answer": "The Red Baron or Manfred von Richthofen"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This party reduced working time to 35 hours per week with the Aubry laws. One winning candidate from this party won on the 110 Propositions, which involved the creation of a solidarity tax on wealth. The first cohabitation took place between that party leader and (20 pts)",
        "Jacques Chirac from 1986-1988. Dominique Strauss-Kahn, the former head of the IMF, was a member of this party, whose current head has stepped up (10 pts)",
        "attacks in the Middle East in response to the Bataclan shootings. For ten points, name this French center-left party, whose leaders have included Francois Mitterand and Francois Hollande."
      ],
      "answer": "Socialist Party of France"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this war, the Treaty of Easton reversed some of the provisions of the Walking Purchase. In this war, James Abercrombie blundered by ordering a frontal assault with no artillery support at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Carillon. During this war, an army landed at L’Anse-au-Foulon then climbed a high cliff under nightfall; in the ensuing battle, opposing generals Louis-Joseph de (10 pts)",
        "Montcalm and James Wolfe died on the Plains of Abraham, leading to the British conquest of Quebec City. For ten points, name this theater of the Seven Years’ War that cemented British North American colonialism."
      ],
      "answer": "French and Indian War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler backed the Occasional Conformity Act to bar Catholics from public office. Abigail Masham replaced this ruler’s friendship with Sarah Churchill. William, Duke of Gloucester was the only (20 pts)",
        "child of this ruler to survive past infancy. The Act of Settlement was passed during this ruler’s reign, establishing Electress Sophia as the heiress (10 pts)",
        "presumptive. For ten points, name this British queen, the last monarch of the House of Stuart, during whose reign the Acts of Union united England and Scotland."
      ],
      "answer": "Queen Anne"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man massacred the crew of the Miri while attempting to force a treaty upon the Zamorin. Nicolau Coelho [ko-way-loh] delivered reports of this man’s successes to Manuel I after the Berrio managed to reach port faster than the flagship (20 pts)",
        "Sao Gabriel. Under the sponsorship of Henry the Navigator, this man landed in (10 pts)",
        "Calicut by following Bartolomeu Dias’ route around the Cape of Good Hope. For ten points, name this first European explorer to reach India by sea."
      ],
      "answer": "Vasco da Gama"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler’s forces were victorious at Kozludzha, allowing for an annexation of the Crimea in the Treaty of Kuchuk Kainarji. Disgruntled peasants attempted to overthrow this ruler in the (20 pts)",
        "Pugachev revolt. Sham villages were allegedly constructed so that Grigory Potemkin could impress this ruler, who was brought to power in a coup against (10 pts)",
        "her husband, Peter III. For ten points, name this patron of Denis Diderot and Voltaire, an enlightened tsarina of Russia."
      ],
      "answer": "Catherine the Great or Catherine II"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These people were targeted in the Weenen massacre. They established the state of Natalia after recovering a lost treaty from the body of their leader, Piet Retief, who had been executed by (20 pts)",
        "Dingaan. Andries Pretorius led these people to victory at the Blood River by utilizing a laager fort against (10 pts)",
        "Zulus seeking to disrupt the Great Trek. These people founded the Orange Free State after leaving the British-held Cape Colony. For ten points, name these Dutch-speaking people of South Africa."
      ],
      "answer": "Boers"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) For his efforts during an attempt at this action, Michel Ney was dubbed the “bravest of the brave.” The truce of Deulino ended a successful instance of this action, which included the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Klushino. A leader fled to the Ottoman Empire after the Great Frost of 1709 doomed an attempt at this action, which ended with a defeat for Adam Leuwenhaupt. A failed attempt at this action was doomed by scorched earth tactics, (10 pts)",
        "Cossacks, and “General Winter.” For ten points, name this difficult military action that Napoleon attempted in 1812."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "invading Russia",
        "elaborations involving French, Polish, and/or Swedish invasions of Russia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Revolt of the Lankans took place in this colony among angry nobles called datus, who were divided into the Puno, Ginoo, and Maginoo. This colony was founded after the conquest of the Moro people and conflicts with (20 pts)",
        "Brunei and Sulu. Ships departing from this colony brought porcelain and china to Acapulco across the Pacific. The discoverer of this colony, (10 pts)",
        "Ferdinand Magellan, died here during the Battle of Mactan. For ten points, name this Spanish colony where galleons brought silver to the port of Manila."
      ],
      "answer": "Philippines or the Spanish East Indies"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The first Boeing 747 to suffer an accident was this airline’s Flight 540 in 1974; 55 people died in Kenya in its worst disaster. In 1977, one of this airline’s planes was stormed by members of GSG 9, ending a hostage crisis by Palestinian hijackers who wanted the release of members of the Red Army (20 pts)",
        "Faction. In 1972, another of this airline’s planes was hijacked, leading to the release of three members of Black September who committed the Munich massacre. (10 pts)",
        "Cologne serves as headquarters for, for ten points, what largest German airline?"
      ],
      "answer": "Deutsche Lufthansa AG"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this battle, one side’s failure to seize the Causeway Heights led to a prompt counterattack from James Scarlett in the South Valley. Colin Campbell’s 93rd Highlander regiment was dubbed the (20 pts)",
        "“Thin Red Line” for their resoluteness in this battle. Lord Raglan ordered the Earl of Cardigan’s cavalry to attack the wrong set of Russian batteries in this battle; that disaster was recounted in a (10 pts)",
        "poem by Alfred, Lord Tennyson. For ten points, name this battle, part of the Siege of Sevastopol during the Crimean War, which featured the Charge of the Light Brigade."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Balaclava"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader’s Anti-Radical Decree prevented communists from taking jobs as teachers. In the midst of negotiating the boundaries of the Oder-Neisse line with Poland, this leader performed the kniefall [”kneefall”] in front of a (20 pts)",
        "monument to victims of the Warsaw Ghetto Uprising. This Social Democrat was forced to resign when his aide, Gunter Guillaume [ghee-ohm], was revealed to be a (10 pts)",
        "Stasi agent from a neighboring country. For ten points, name this West German chancellor who won the 1971 Nobel Peace Prize for his practice of ostpolitik."
      ],
      "answer": "Willy Brandt"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The court of this king resolved a disputation in which Nicholas Donin pressed charges of blasphemy against the Talmud. This king allowed Henry III to keep his conquests in Aquitaine despite defeating him at (20 pts)",
        "Taillebourg. During a campaign, this king was captured by the troops of Baibars and Qutuz. Damietta was given to the Mamluks in exchange for the release of this king following the Battle of Al-Mansurah. This king died of dysentery in modern-day (10 pts)",
        "Tunisia while leading the Eighth Crusade. For ten points, name this only French monarch to be canonized."
      ],
      "answer": "Louis IX or Saint Louis"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This group formed the Confederation of Cologne and conducted a bombardment of Copenhagen, forcing Valdemar IV to grant them increased privileges. This group was plagued by the forces of Albert of Mecklenburg and the (20 pts)",
        "Victual Brothers, and it suffered a setback when Ivan III shut down their operations in Novgorod. This group was prominent in Bergen and Stralsund, but it was dominated by (10 pts)",
        "Lu¨beck in its early stages. A series of kontor trading posts was administered by, for ten points, what Northern European merchants guild formed during the Late Middle Ages?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Hanseatic League",
        "Hansa"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Hostilities that this treaty failed to end were later resolved through the Treaties of Baden and Rastatt. Under this treaty, 200 years after Tordesillas, Portugal’s control of Brazil was finally recognized. Great Britain gained (20 pts)",
        "Gibraltar and the asiento, a monopoly on the slave trade, through this treaty. Under this treaty, a claim to the (10 pts)",
        "French throne was renounced by Philip of Anjou so that he could be king of an Iberian country. For ten points, name this treaty that ended the War of Spanish Succession."
      ],
      "answer": "Treaty or Peace, etc. of Utrecht"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During the disposal of this man’s body, his assassins drove a Fiat truck into the Koptyaki forest only to realize they had only one shovel. This man received notice that Leonid Sednev would be leaving his entourage shortly before he was (20 pts)",
        "moved into the basement of the Ipatiev House in Yekaterinburg. (10 pts)",
        "Anastasia was speculated to have survived the murder of this man and his family. Fearing the advancing White Army, the Bolsheviks executed, for ten points, what final Russian tsar?"
      ],
      "answer": "Nicholas II"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Description acceptable. A pessimistic analysis of this event was criticized by Etienne Mantoux’s [eh-tee-ehn mahn-too’s] Carthaginian Peace. Government price controls developed in the aftermath of this event led to (20 pts)",
        "hyperinflation, one of this event’s Economic Consequences detailed by John Maynard Keynes; that analysis of this event was cited by the (10 pts)",
        "“irreconcilables,” who thus argued against joining the League of Nations as part of this event. For ten points, name this event that led to the creation of the Weimar Republic and the imposition of severe reparations against the defeated Germany."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "the agreements to end World War I",
        "descriptive answers relating to the peace process that ended World War I",
        "the signing of the Treaty of Versailles",
        "the Paris Peace Conference",
        "descriptions that relate to the US’s rejection of Versailles/signing a separate peace to end World War I, etc."
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the Treaty of Ryswick, Spain formally recognized French control of Acadia and a colony in this location. In this location, the one-armed Fran¸cois Mackandal led raids on plantation owners. Shortly before the dissolution of a colony here, it was struck by an outbreak of (20 pts)",
        "yellow fever that killed general Charles Leclerc. A decade-long slave revolt here was led by figures like (10 pts)",
        "Jean-Jacques Dessalines and Toussaint Louverture. The French colony of Saint-Domingue [sahn doh-MEENG] was located in, for ten points, what modern-day country on the western half of Hispaniola?"
      ],
      "answer": "Haiti"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This nation’s diplomats were forced to attend a peace conference held atop barges after they suffered defeats at the Battles of Eylau and Friedland. After violating the subsequent treaty, this nation used the (20 pts)",
        "Unicorn artillery piece, the Bagration Fleches, and the Raevsky redoubt to defend its home soil at (10 pts)",
        "Borodino. Because this nation refused to follow the Treaty of Tilsit and join the Continental System against Britain, it was invaded in 1812. A harsh winter helped thwart Napoleon’s invasion of, for ten points, what country led by Tsar Alexander I?"
      ],
      "answer": "Russian Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A key site of fighting during this battle was the Wo¨evre [wheh-vre] plain, where the Germans overran Fort Vaux [voh] after having captured Fort Douaumont with little resistance. Thousands of men and vehicles were shuttled along the (20 pts)",
        "Sacred Way to this battle, where Erich von Falkenhayn wanted to inflict the maximum number of casualties on the (10 pts)",
        "French. Phillipe Petain’s leadership earned him the epithet “the Lion of,” For ten points, what 1916 battle along the Meuse River, the longest of World War I?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Verdun"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Syagrius lost the Battle of Soissons [swah-sohn] to a ruler of these people, who also beat the Visigoths at the Battle of Vouill´e [VOO-ye]. Subgroups of these people included the Ripuarians and the Salians. After the Battle of Tertry, the (20 pts)",
        "Arnulfing Clan of these people grew power as Mayors of the Palace. A ruler of these people was crowned by Pope Leo III on Christmas Day. This group included the (10 pts)",
        "Merovingian Dynasty and its leaders included Pepin the Short and Clovis. Charlemagne was a leader of, for ten points, what Germanic group that eventually settled in Gaul?"
      ],
      "answer": "Franks"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man created a branch of philosophy inspired by Jan Jakob Maria de Groot called Universism. During the Great Depression, this defense minister sent troops to break the Menstad conflict, and as prime minister, he created the (20 pts)",
        "Hirden paramilitary. Following the German invasion of his country in Operation Weser Exercise, this man launched a coup via radio broadcast. This man was executed in (10 pts)",
        "Akershus Fortress in 1945 after he collaborated with the SS in the Holocaust. The Nasjonal Samling party was led by, for ten points, what infamous Norwegian traitor?"
      ],
      "answer": "Vidkun Quisling"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s brief, post-war second term as mayor ended when Gerald Templer fired him for “laziness and incompetence.” This politician aimed to pull the Zentrum “out of the tower” by uniting Protestants and Catholics in one party. The Miracle on the (20 pts)",
        "Rhine was caused by this man’s finance minister, Ludwig Erhard. This leader, who defeated rival Kurt Schumacher in a 1949 election, controversially suggested that (10 pts)",
        "Bonn, not Frankfurt, be made his provisional capital. For ten points, name this founder of the Christian Democratic Union, the first Chancellor of West Germany."
      ],
      "answer": "Konrad Adenauer"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Two answers required. An intervention in a war between these two countries was the subject of the Simla Manifesto, promising to restore Shah Shuja. Louis Cavagnari served as a diplomat from one of these two countries to the other but was killed in riots after the 1879 Treaty of (20 pts)",
        "Gandamak paused a war between these two countries; after those riots, Abdur Rahman Khan was installed as Emir. One of these countries imposed the (10 pts)",
        "Durand Line on the other as its border with modern Pakistan. For ten points, name these two countries that fought three wars in the 19th and 20th centuries, the last of which ended with a European power vacating Kabul."
      ],
      "answer": "Emirate of Afghanistan and the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Sich autonomous state was created for these people in the Treaty of Pereyaslav, which was signed in the wake of the Khmelnytsky [k’mel-nit-skee] uprising against Polish- Lithuanian control. These people extended their reach to the (20 pts)",
        "Terek and Yaik after allying with government forces, but their ranks also included rebellious leaders like Stenka Razin and Yemelyan (10 pts)",
        "Pugachev. This group was predominantly centered around the Dnieper and Don rivers. For ten points, name these autonomous horsemen who served as police and military units in 19th century Russia."
      ],
      "answer": "Cossacks"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Women’s Death Battalion supported this man against a 1917 coup by his enemies. This man gained fame reporting on the Lena Goldfields Massacre. This Trudovik names an offensive against Austria-Hungary that is also called the July Offensive. After the (20 pts)",
        "Kornilov affair, this man became Commander in Chief; earlier, he replaced Prince Lvov as Prime Minister. A movement against this man called for (10 pts)",
        "“peace, land and bread” and led to the October Revolution. For ten points, name this leader of the Russian Provisional Government who was ousted by the Bolsheviks under Lenin."
      ],
      "answer": "Alexander Kerensky"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One leader of this political party tried to restore order with his “Back to Basics” campaign, which backfired after many of his ministers were caught in extramarital affairs. Another leader of this political party lost power in 1974 to a minority-power government led by (20 pts)",
        "Harold Wilson. Yet another leader of this party conducted a namesake program of privatizing government companies, was the target of the (10 pts)",
        "Brighton Hotel bombing, and was nicknamed “the Iron Lady.” Margaret Thatcher belonged to, for ten points, what British political party?"
      ],
      "answer": "Conservative and Unionist Party"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After this battle, Moses Hazen accidentally threatened to hang Charles Asgill, causing an international ruckus. This battle’s losers failed to retreat to Gloucester Point and lost their supply line following the destruction of Thomas (20 pts)",
        "Graves’ fleet. In the aftermath of this battle, Charles O’Hara was told to give his sword to Benjamin Lincoln as the tune “The (10 pts)",
        "World Turned Upside Down” played. The Comte de Rochambeau helped trap a British force in, for ten points, what decisive battle of the Revolutionary War where Cornwallis surrendered?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Yorktown"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler commissioned Comte de la Perouse’s failed circumnavigation of the world, and his admiral Pierre de Suffren allied the Mysores against England. This monarch, who appointed Charles de Calonne as Finance Minister two years after dismissing (20 pts)",
        "Jacques Necker, reversed the Edict of Fontainebleau to grant religious freedom in the Edict of Versailles. Members of the (10 pts)",
        "Third Estate united in a tennis court during the reign of, for ten points, what French king who married Marie Antoinette and was guillotined in the French Revolution?"
      ],
      "answer": "Louis XVI"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man escaped hidden in an oak tree at the Battle of Worcester. As part of the Clarendon Code passed by this man, non-Anglican Church Ministers had to stay five miles away from towns. (20 pts)",
        "Titus Oates invented a fictitious plot to kill this monarch in the Popish Plot. The Convention Parliament welcomed this king, who began the English (10 pts)",
        "Restoration. For ten points, name this king who ruled after Oliver Cromwell, who had earlier ordered the execution of his father after the English Civil War."
      ],
      "answer": "Charles II"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A monk in this work claims that The Palaces of the Patriarch is the setting of the seventh scene of this play, in which Pimen writes a history of his native country. Nikolay Karamzin was one of the writers who inspired this (20 pts)",
        "1825 work, in which an army is led by Grigory against the title character, who had previously served as a boyar before the death of (10 pts)",
        "Dmitri. The Time of Troubles is the background of, for ten points, what play about a Russian tsar, written by Alexander Pushkin?"
      ],
      "answer": "Boris Godunov"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Richard Fletcher took orders from this man to build the massive Lines of Torres Vedras. This man, who led the reserves at the Battle of Seringapatam in 1799, was opposed by Anthony Pohlmann, who commanded forces for the (20 pts)",
        "Maratha ruler Raghuji Bhonsle II, at the Battle of Assaye. During the Peninsular War, this general defeated French forces at the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Salamanca, and this man joined Gebhard von Blucher in a key victory in Belgium that led to an emperor being exiled to St. Helena. For ten points, name this British general who won the 1815 Battle of Waterloo over Napoleon."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Arthur Wellesley, first Duke of Wellington",
        "either",
        "both underlined names"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After this man failed to gain support for a bill legalizing denomination-based boarding schools, he was replaced in his post by Botho zu Eulenburg. The Agrarian League opposed this man for his support of free trade. Though he was able to secure Heligoland in an exchange for (20 pts)",
        "Zanzibar, this man failed to renew his predecessor’s Reinsurance Treaty with Russia. This man’s “New Course” policy aimed to improve relations with Great Britain, who ceded a (10 pts)",
        "Namibian strip named for this man to Germany. For ten points, name this successor of Otto von Bismarck as chancellor."
      ],
      "answer": "Leo von Caprivi"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The name of the central group in this event was inspired by a French saying meaning “Comrade, let’s get a drink.” A man known as Ser Nuto was hung by one foot during this event. The Eight Saints were defeated during this event, whose leader was chosen after he walked barefoot into a palace. A group of (20 pts)",
        "butchers carried out an attack in the Piazza della Signoria during this event. Michele [mik-ay-lay] di Lando became the (10 pts)",
        "Gonfaloniere during this event, which was partly caused by anger at the quadrupling of guild entry fees. For ten points, name this 1378 revolt of Florentine woolworkers."
      ],
      "answer": "Ciompi Revolt"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this battle, the losing commander devised an attrition strategy known as Operation Judgement. To end this battle, Charles Mangin helped one side recapture a location that the losers captured without firing a shot on this battle’s third day, (20 pts)",
        "Fort Douaumont. Control of the Meuse Heights was a central goal of Erich Falkenhayn during this battle, which began roughly three months prior to the Battle of the (10 pts)",
        "Somme. The German plan to “bleed [the French] white” failed at, for ten points, what longest battle of World War I’s Western Front?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Verdun"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man attempted to secure power by forcing his nobles to swear the Salisbury Oath. This ruler’s suppression of the revolt of Edgar the Aetheling was so destructive that the campaign became known as the (20 pts)",
        "“Harrying of the North.” This man accounted for landholdings in his territory by ordering the compilation of the (10 pts)",
        "Domesday [“doomsday”] Book. The Bayeux Tapestry depicts the death of Harold Godwinson at the hands of this man’s archers. For ten points, name this Norman duke who was crowned King of England after his 1066 victory at Hastings."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "William I of England",
        "William the Conqueror",
        "William the Bastard",
        "William of Normandy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Controversies flared over the necessity of HOM, PP, and IT redactions in this document. After the release of this document, Jerry Nadler subpoenaed a former White House Counsel to testify before the House Judiciary Committee. (20 pts)",
        "Kellyanne Conway called for apologies in the wake of this document, whose redacted form was published by Attorney General William (10 pts)",
        "Barr. Rod Rosenstein commissioned this document after Jeff Sessions recused himself in 2017. For ten points, name this Special Council investigation report prepared by a former FBI director concerning Russian interference in the 2016 election."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Mueller Report",
        "Report on the Investigation into Russian Interference in the 2016 Presidential Election"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Insane lumberjack Daniel M’Naghten sought to kill this man, but shot his secretary, Edward Drummond, instead. As Prime Minister, this man issued the Tamworth Manifesto, which laid the groundwork for the modern (20 pts)",
        "Conservative Party. This man’s refusal to succeed Lord Melbourne caused the Bedchamber Crisis. This man established the (10 pts)",
        "Metropolitan Police in London and inspired their nickname of “bobbies.” For ten points, name this 19th century British Prime Minister who repealed the Corn Laws."
      ],
      "answer": "Sir Robert Peel"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Before funding this technology, Hugh Dowding demanded evidence and was impressed by the Daventry Experiment. America’s knowledge of this technology improved after Henry Tizard’s British delegation delivered a better (20 pts)",
        "cavity magnetron. To hide the existence of this technology, a British propaganda campaign claimed that foods rich in Vitamin A, like (10 pts)",
        "carrots, improved night vision. The Chain Home stations used this technology to provide advance warning of Luftwaffe attacks. For ten points, name this detection technology that bounces radio waves off of incoming aircraft."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "radar",
        "radio detection and ranging"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While jailed in Occitania, this man wrote \"No Man is Imprisoned,\" after which he was moved to Trifels Castle despite Pope Celestine II's threat of excommunication. This ruler was captured by Leopold of Austria for having killed Conrad of Montferrat [[monh-feh-RAH]] before being ransomed by (20 pts)",
        "Emperor Henry VI. This ruler died at Chalus-Chambrol [[shah-LOO shahm-BROHL]] after warring with his former friend and ally, Philip Augustus of France. The co-signer of the Treaty of Jaffa with (10 pts)",
        "Saladin, for ten points, who was this king of England during the Third Crusade?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Richard I or Richard the Lionhearted",
        "or Richard, Coeur de Lion"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This left-wing figure used the pseudonym \"Gunnar Gaasland\" while living in Norway until the rise of the Quisling government. This head of the SPD resigned after his aide, Günter Guillaume [[gee-YOHM]], was outed as a secret agent for the (*) Stasi [[SHTAH-see]]. This chancellor collapsed weeping at the Warsaw Ghetto monument while on a state visit to Poland. This man won the 1971 Nobel (*) Peace Prize for his work to strengthen European cooperation. For ten points, name this West German chancellor who pursued Ostpolitik while attempting to reconcile with East Germany."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Willy Brandt",
        "Herbert Ernst Karl Frahm 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 7"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Jacques Massu evoked this government’s name for his short-lived 1950s military junta during the Algiers Putsch. This government was created by the National Convention to supplement the Committee of General Defence and was initially led by perfume dealer Maximin Isnard, a (20 pts)",
        "Girondist, until his 1793 flight from Paris. This government was deposed during the Thermidorian Reaction, and it ruled at the height of the (10 pts)",
        "“Reign of Terror.” For ten points, name this “Committee” during the French Revolution led by Maximilian Robespierre."
      ],
      "answer": "Committee of Public Safety or Comité de salut public"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Medieval historian Roger of Wendover claimed that this man offered to convert to Islam if Muhammad al-Nasir lent him military support. This man's refusal to appoint sub-prior Reginald to the post of Archbishop of (20 pts)",
        "Canterbury led to his temporary excommunication by Innocent III. This king was temporarily deposed by the French King, Louis the Lion, after he captured half of England during the First (10 pts)",
        "Barons' War. For ten points, name this brother of Richard the Lionheart and signer of the Magna Carta."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "King John",
        "John Lackland"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Robert Burnell served as chancellor to this king, who enforced substitution as the only means of alienating lands by the terms of the statute, Quia Emptores. Oliver Cromwell overturned a policy set by this man that removed one ethnic group over suspicion of blood libel, as well as their practice of usury. The Edict of (20 pts)",
        "Expulsion of the Jews was passed by this man, whose forces were defeated at the Battle of Stirling Bridge. This son of Henry III captured and hanged William (10 pts)",
        "Wallace of Scotland. For ten points, name this English king who was nicknamed for his height."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Edward I of England",
        "Edward Longshanks"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Many native names in this language come from a tradition known as the \"Dream Name,\" where a name is chosen by a pregnant mother after a visitor appears to her while asleep. This language, which has an official committee on what children can be (20 pts)",
        "named, formed an unusual pidgin with Basque due to Iberian whalers needing to communicate with locals. Snorri Sturluson wrote the Prose Edda in an early form of this tongue, describing the creation of the Aesir [[AY-seer]]. Old (10 pts)",
        "Norse is most-closely related to, for ten points, what Germanic language spoken in Reykjavík?"
      ],
      "answer": "Icelandic or Islenska"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Before assuming his most notable position, this man was told \"May God curse your studies\" during a recruitment attempt by future ally William Farel. This theologian helped build the case of heresy against Michael (20 pts)",
        "Cervetus, who was then burned at the stake. This reformer pleaded with Francis I to stop persecuting the Huguenots in his native country in the preface to his magnum opus, (10 pts)",
        "Institutes of the Christian Religion. For ten points, name this French-Swiss reformer who expounded the doctrine of predestination while living in Geneva."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "John Calvin or Jean Calvin",
        "Jean Cauvin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Johann Gustav Droysen wrote the seven volume work The History of [this state's] Politics and led it's namesake school of historiography in the 19th century. The treatise On (20 pts)",
        "War was written by a military theorist and general from this kingdom, Carl von Clausewitz. Count Mirabeau [[me-rah-BOH]] once stated this kingdom was \"not a state with a (10 pts)",
        "military, but a military with a state.\" For ten points, name this early modern state which united Germany in the 19th century under the leadership of Otto von Bismarck."
      ],
      "answer": "Kingdom of Prussia or Königreich Preussen"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While in the King's Privy chamber, this figure gave the pseudonym John Johnson and was asked questions such as \"When and where he learned to speak French?\" This man, whose body parts were paraded around (20 pts)",
        "London after his execution, was outed by an anonymous letter which told English authorities to look for him in the Palace of Westminster. This man is burned in effigy on a namesake holiday on November (10 pts)",
        "5th. For ten points, name this English Catholic member of the Gunpowder Plot who attempted to blow up the House of Lords in 1605."
      ],
      "answer": "Guy Fawkes or Guido Fawkes"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A note supposedly written by the subject of this event was found in the wastebasket of Prussian attaché Maximilian von Schwartzkoppen, only for that German officer to later reveal he was in contact with Ferdinand (20 pts)",
        "Esterhazy. Following this affair, future prime minister Leon Blum participated in the defense of Emile Zola after he was brought to court for criticizing this treason trial in his pamphlet (10 pts)",
        "J'Accuse. For ten points, name this anti-Semitic \"Affair\" during the French Third Republic caused by the false prosecution of a Jewish artillery officer."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Dreyfus Affair",
        "l'affaire Dreyfus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Sergei Eisenstein used this historical figure in his 1938 film as an allegory to the deteriorating relationship between Nazi Germany and his native USSR. After being sent into exile by the boyars, (20 pts)",
        "this man returned to lead native forces against the invading Livonian Order at the behest of Novgorod. During that campaign, this general, supported by the Pskov Republic, defeated the Teutonic Knights on the frozen Lake Peipus [[PIE-puhs]] during the Battle on the (10 pts)",
        "Ice. For ten points, name this Russian folk hero of the 13th century, a Grand Prince of Kiev."
      ],
      "answer": "Alexander Nevsky or Alexander Yaroslavich Nevsky"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A work about this entity uses Byzantine annals by George Hamartolus and John of Malalas. Histories of this polity are in the Radziwill Chronicle, including the Tale of Bygone Years. A monk from the Monastery of the Caves, Nestor, compiled this realm's history, which is in the (20 pts)",
        "Hypatian and Laurentian Codices. The Primary Chronicle of this political entity begins with the Severians fighting Viking brothers Sineus, Truvor and (10 pts)",
        "Rurik, the founder of Novgorod. For ten points, name this loose federation of Eastern European peoples, ruled by Vladimir the Great."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Kievan Rus' or Rusĭ",
        "Ruthenia"
      ]
    }
  ]
}